<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_540">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>D. 6</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Near and Middle Eastern Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Cambridge University Library</addrLine>
                  <street>West Road</street>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <postCode>CB3 9DR</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/deptserv/neareastern/">Cambridge University Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">D_6</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="D_6" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Cambridgeshire</region>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution>Cambridge University</institution>
                  <repository>University Library</repository>
                  <collection>E. G. Browne Collection</collection>
                  <idno>D. 6</idno>
                  <altIdentifier change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <idno>D. 6 (10).</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <p>مقدمه فهرست مثنوی در احوال مولوی معنوی</p>
                     <p>A table of the entire contents of the Mathnawi (ff. 128-170), to which is <lb/>
                            prefixed (ff. 1-124) a very interesting critical examination of Súfi doctrine in <lb/>
                            general and of the teachings of the Mathnatel in particular, with especial regard to <lb/>
                            the charges of heresy levelled against them by certain Shi'a theologians, especially <lb/>
                            Mullá Muhammad Tahir of Qum <note>His biography is given in the Rawdátu'l-Jannát (pp. 336-337), but not the date of his death. He <lb/>
                            was very bitter against the Súfis, and had many controversies with Mullá Muhammad Taqi-i-Majlisi on <lb/>
                            the subject.</note>, composed by Muhammad Shafi, son of the <lb/>
                            eminent Shaykh Bahá'u'd Din al-'Amili, about the year 1185/1771-2 <note>This date is mentioned on f. 121b as the current date at the time of writing.</note>. The earlier <lb/>
                            portion of these Prolegomena (to f. 8a) deals chiefly with the various reproaches <lb/>
                            (a) brought against Jalálu'd-Din Rúmi by his detractors and the replies to <lb/>
                            them made by his defenders, both sides being stated very fairly. Thus an attempt <lb/>
                            is made in ch. 1 (f. 10b) to prove that he was a Shi'a; in chs. II and III (ff. 11 and <lb/>
                            13) to explain away his apparent apology for Ibn Muljam, the murderer of 'Ali, <lb/>
                            whom he represents as acting under the compulsion of a fate which he cannot <lb/>
                            escape, and as being comforted by his victim with a promise of intercession at the <lb/>
                            Last Day:</p>
                     <p>ليك بيغم شو شفیع تو منم</p>
                     <p>خواجه</p>
                     <p>نه مملوك تغم... <lb/>
                            روحم</p>
                     <p>ز آنکه این را من نمیدانم ز تو <lb/>
                            بغضی نیست در جانم ز تو <lb/>
                            هیچ</p>
                     <p>Ch. IV (f. 17), a very long one, deals with the doctrine of Pantheism (Waḥdatu <lb/>
                            -Wujild), and cites the opinions of a number of thinkers, such as Shaykh <lb/>
                            Shabistari, his commentator Láhijí, Mír Dámád, Jámí, Jalálu'd-Din Dawání, <lb/>
                            Muḥammad Báqir-i-Majlisí, etc. No further chapters seem to be indicated until <lb/>
                            we reach the conclusion (Khatima, f. 82), containing short notices of eminent <lb/>
                            Súfis and philosophers from the earliest times (Uways al-Qaraní, Kumayl, Hasan <lb/>
                            of Başra, Málik Dínár, Dhu'n-Nún of Egypt, Báyazid of Bistám, al-Halláj, etc.) <lb/>
                            down to Shaykh Bahá'u'd-Din al-Amili, Mir Abu'l-Qasim-i-Findariski, Mulla <lb/>
                            Sadra, Mulla Muhsin-i-Fayd, and other notable thinkers of the Safawi period. <lb/>
                            This book contains a great deal of interesting material, and would well deserve <lb/>
                            fuller study. Begins after the Bismi'lláh (f. 1¹):</p>
                     <p>لولا لمعات شمس نور الكرم <lb/>
                            لولا نفحات عطر روض القدم <lb/>
                            والعالم في جب ظلام العدم 1 ما كان من الوجود قطعا أثر،</p>
                     <p>هستی نبود آنچه درین ارض و سماست <lb/>
                            عالم همه موجود ز اسماء خداست</p>
                     <p>نبود چو فروغ مهر پرتو بکجاست <lb/>
                            پیدائی ذرات از خورشید بود</p>
                     <p>After the doxology, which fills the best part of three pages, the author mentions <lb/>
                            his name as follows (f. 2, penultimate line):</p>
                     <p>و بعد بعرض ناظران این کلام و مطالعه کنندگان این ارقام میرساند خادم صفه نشینان <lb/>
                            بارگاه اهل معنی ابن المرحوم بهاء الدين محمد العاملى محمد شفيع الحسيني كه صورت این <lb/>
                            خیال چنین در مرات خاطر مرتسم کردید ... الخ</p>
                     <p>The author then enumerates (f. 3) a number of authorities of whom he has made <lb/>
                            use, and expresses his desire to write dispassionately and without prejudice about <lb/>
                            the Mathnawi, of which he is neither the indiscriminate admirer nor the hostile <lb/>
                            critic:</p>
                     <p>الحاصل راقم اينحروف كه نه مادح مثنوی معنوی و نه قادح مولوی رومی است خواست که <lb/>
                            کتاب مثنوی را بنظر انصاف بدون عصبیت و اعتساف بیند و گلهای فوایدش را چیند</p>
                     <p>In his notice of Sháh Ni'matu'lláh (ff. 96b-98a) the author quotes a curious poem <lb/>
                            in which that eminent gnostic is said to have foretold the names and reigns of all <lb/>
                            the Safawi kings. It begins:</p>
                     <p>غصه و غم از زمین تا آسمان خواهد گرفت <lb/>
                            ای عزیزان شور و غوغا در جهان خواهد گرفت <lb/>
                            فاش در عالم همه راز نهان خواهد گرفت <lb/>
                            چون ز هجرت نهصد و نه سال و کسری بگذرد <lb/>
                            خاک پایش در جهان کحل عیان خواهد گرفت <lb/>
                            شاه اسمعیل بن حيدر بوده باشد شهریار</p>
                     <p>and ends:</p>
                     <p>آنچه از امروز تا آخر زمان خواهد گرفت <lb/>
                            از کلام حق و قبول مصطفى كويم خبرا</p>
                     <p>These Arabic verses are marked in red (by the author), and the succeeding Persian quatrain</p>
                     <p>.(by the copyist لمسوده</p>
                     <p>اسمعیل حیدر The metre requires]</p>
                     <p>The author then sketches the history of the Safawis down to the end of the dynasty, <lb/>
                            and alludes to the subsequent reigns of Nádir Sháh and Karim Khán-i-Zand, and <lb/>
                            to his rivals Ázád Khán the Afghán and Muhammad Hasan Khan-i-Qájár</p>
                     <p>The MS. comprises 171 f. of 23 x 14'5 c. and 21 ll. The Prolegomena <lb/>
                            (ff. 1-124) are written in a neat Persian ta'liq with rubrications and numerous <lb/>
                            marginal indications of topics which greatly facilitate reference: the titles and <lb/>
                            numerous Arabic citations are in a larger naskh hand, and generally in red. This <lb/>
                            part of the book ends abruptly with the title:</p>
                     <p>عارف ربانی آقا محمد بیدآبادی اصفهانی</p>
                     <p>followed by an erasure of the remaining half page. The Table of Contents <lb/>
                            (ff. 128-170) is written in four columns, partly in red in the naskh, and partly in <lb/>
                            black in the ta'liq hand. The date 1178/1764-5 occurring in the colophon must <lb/>
                            apparently be taken as the date when the work was begun.</p>
                  </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="D_6-item1">
                     <author key="person_51453822" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/51453822/">
                        <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" type="standard">Ḥusaynī ʻĀmilī, Muḥammad Shafīʻ ibn Bahāʾ al-Dīn, 18th cent.</persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">حسيني عاملي، محمد شافع بن بهاء الدين</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc" key="work_581">Muqaddima-yi fihrist-i mas̲navī dar aḥvāl-i mawlavī-i maʻnavī</title>
                     <title xml:lang="fa" key="work_581">مقدمۀ فهرست مثنوی در احوال مولوی معنوی</title>
                     <note>Includes a critical examination of the Sūfī doctrines, with especial regard to the charges of heresy levelled against them.</note>
                     <incipit xml:lang="ar"/>
                     <explicit xml:lang="ar" defective="true"/>
                     <note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar"/>
                     </note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="https://cudl.lib.cam.ac.uk/view/PR-A-00233-00004/54">p.28</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl type="text-relations">Introduction to and table of contexts of the <title xml:lang="fa-Latn-xlc">Mas̲navī maʻnavī <foreign xml:lang="fa">مثنوي معنوي</foreign>
                           </title> of <author key="person_98930150"
                                   ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/98930150/"
                                   role="ant"
                                   change="#role-assignment">
                              <persName xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc">Jalāl al-Dīn Rūmī, Maulana, 1207-1273 <persName xml:lang="fa">مولانا جلال الدين رومى</persName>
                              </persName>
                           </author>.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="fa">Persian</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc change="#ai-catalogue">
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <support>Paper</support>
                        <extent>Ff. 171 <dimensions unit="cm">
                              <height>23</height>
                              <width>14.5</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout>
                           <p>21 lines</p>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="taliq">Neat Persian ta'liq with rubrications; titles and Arabic citations in larger naskh, generally in red.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  
                  <origin change="#fix-dates">
                     <origDate notBefore="1764" notAfter="1765" calendar="#Hijri-qamari">1178</origDate>
                     <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" when="1764">1764-5</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance change="#added-content">
                     One of the <persName key="person_f7815" role="fmo">Belshah</persName> MSS, bought in 1920. 
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bequest of <persName xml:lang="en"
                               type="standard"
                               key="person_29651479"
                               ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29651479/"
                               role="fmo"
                               change="#role-assignment">E. G. Browne</persName>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source> Summary, physical description and provenance copied from <ref target="https://cudl.lib.cam.ac.uk/view/PR-A-00233-00004/1">R. A.
            Nicholson: <hi rend="italic">A descriptive catalogue of the Oriental MSS belonging to the late E.G.
            Browne</hi>. Cambridge, 1932</ref>.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/cgi-bin/eligibility.cgi/">Cambridge University Library Admissions</ref>). Contact <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh2008112367"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh2008112367#concept">Sufism--Early works to 1800</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85100085"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85100085#concept">Persian poetry--747-1500</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85121391"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85121391#concept">Shīʻah--Doctrines</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025" xml:id="check-ai"><persName>Syed Gillani</persName></change>
         <change when="2025-06-04" xml:id="ai-catalogue">Values generated from legacy catalogue using a combination of AI and manual editing.</change>
         <change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="role-assignment">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName> Assigned role(s) to every person having an id (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2018-06-08">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Updated key attributes using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/update-keys.xsl">update-keys.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-15" xml:id="add-summary">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Added summary using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/add-summaries.xsl">add-summaries.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-02" xml:id="fix-dates">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Added or modified attributes in origDate elements using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/fix-dates.xsl">fix-dates.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-07-28">
            <persName>Ignacio Sanchez</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
