<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_735">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>J. 21</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Near and Middle Eastern Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Cambridge University Library</addrLine>
                  <street>West Road</street>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <postCode>CB3 9DR</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/deptserv/neareastern/">Cambridge University Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">J_21</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="J_21" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Cambridgeshire</region>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution>Cambridge University</institution>
                  <repository>University Library</repository>
                  <collection>E. G. Browne Collection</collection>
                  <idno>J. 21</idno>
                  <altIdentifier change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <idno>J. 21 (12)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#translation">
                  <summary change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <p>قصص الانبياء</p>
                     <p>Qifagwl-Anbiya (Tales of the Prophets) translated into Persian by Muhammad <lb/> ibn As'ad ibn 'Abdi'lláh al-Hanafi at-Tustarí, beginning:</p>
                     <p>سباس بی</p>
                     <p>ستایش بی عدد خالقی را کی جندین هزار نقطهٔ نبوت را از مرکز عدم در دایره حد و <lb/> وجود جهت ارشاد خلایق بظهور رسانيد الخ ... جنین گوید بنده ضعيف محمد بن اسعد بن عبد <lb/> الله الحنفى التسترى عفا الله عنه كه جون طباع سلیمه را بخواندن و شنودن احوال گذشتگان و اسماء <lb/> و قصص ایشان شعفی تمام میباشد الخ</p>
                     <p>The name of the author of the Arabic original is given in the Preface as Shaykh <lb/> Abu'l-Hasan ibnu'l-Hayşam (? Haytham) al-Búshanjí, of whom I have hitherto <lb/> found no other mention <note>[He may be identified with Abú Nu'aym Hamza ibnu'l-Haysam al-Búshanji at-Tamimi, who is <lb/> mentioned by Sam'ání, Ansáb, p. 433, l. 20.]</note>. A note by Mr E. Edwards of the British Museum expresses <lb/> the opinion that this work is probably identical with that mentioned by Hájji <lb/> Khalifa (vol. IV, p. 518) and by him ascribed to Sahl ibn 'Abdi'lláh at-Tustarí, but <lb/> states that it is not identical with the British Museum MS. Add. 25.783. The chief</p>
                     <p>contents are indicated by rubrications and are as follows: the Creation, f. 4º; <lb/> Paradise, f. 7b; the Sun, Moon and Stars, f. 10; Iblis, f. 14; Adam, f. 15b; Cain <lb/> and Abel, f. 22"; Idrís (Enoch), f. 24"; Hárút and Márút, f. 27; Noah, f. 29"; <lb/> Ad, f. 32; Thamúd, f. 36; Abraham, f. 40; Lot, f. 49; Ishmael, f. 52; Jacob, <lb/> f. 56 Joseph, f. 58; Job, f. 79; Moses, f. 83"; Dhu'l-Kifl, f. 102"; Samuel, <lb/> f. to; David, f. 105: Solomon, f. 116; Bilqis (the Queen of Sheba), f. 119; <lb/> Laqmán, f. 130: Jonah, f. 135: Ezra, f. 145; Zakariyya and John the Baptist, <lb/> f. 146; Jesus, f. 149; his Disciples, f. 158; the Ashabu'l-Kahf, or ، Seven <lb/> Sleepers," f. 160; Dhu'l-Qarnayn, f. 176; Barṣiṣá, f. 178b; the Ashabul-Ukhdúd, <lb/> f. 182; Jirjís, f. 184"; Paul, f. 189"; Samson, f. 189; the Tubba's, or Kings of <lb/> Yaman, f. 19o'; the Prophet Muhammad, f. 195</p>
                     <p>The account given of St Paul is particularly curious, since he is made responsible <lb/> for the schisms amongst the followers of Christ, and, indeed, plays exactly the same <lb/> part as the Jewish wazir in the second story of the First Book of the Mathnawi. <lb/> This passage is as follows <note>[The text and translation of this passage were published in the last article written by Browne <lb/> before his death, entitled "A parallel to the Story in the Mathnawi of Jalálu'd-Dín Rúmi of the Jewish <lb/> King who persecuted the Christians" (Islamica, vol. II, fasc. i, pp. 129-134), which forms part of the <lb/> "Festschrift" in honour of Professor A. Fischer of Leipzig.]</note>:</p>
                     <p>بخواب دیدم</p>
                     <p>ذكر بولس قال الله تعالى فاختلف الأحزاب من بينهم اهل اخبار گويند که بعد از آنك حق <lb/> تعالی عیسی را بآسمان برد ترسایان طریقه نیکو داشتند تا آنگاه که بولس ایشان را از راه برد و او <lb/> مردی بود از جهودان و با عیسی و اهل ملت او بد بودی و پیوسته مساوی ایشان گفتی و دشمنی <lb/> کردی چون پیر شد گفت که نخواهم که شر من از ایشان منقطع شود پس يك چشم خودرا كور <lb/> کرد و ترسایانرا گفت مرا میشناسید گفتند بلی بدترین خلق خدا توئی گفت من دوش عیسی را <lb/> بخواب دیدم و عیسی دست بر چشم من زد و مرا کور کرد و گفت تا کی اهل ملت مرا برنجانی من بلرزیدم <lb/> و از خواب بر جستم يك چشم من از کار افتاده است پیش شما آمدم تا دین و ملت شما گیرم تا <lb/> عیسی از من خشنود شود که من طاقت عتاب او ندارم ترسایان او را قبول کردند و بخانه بردند <lb/> و او طریقه رهبانان پیش گرفت و همه روز روزه داشتی و همه شب نماز کردی چندانك مردم برو <lb/> فتنه شدند آنگاه گروهی را بخواند و گفت شما نه بینید که لشکر از پیش ملک آید گفتند بلی گفت <lb/> ما میبینیم که آفتاب و ماه و ستارگان از مشرق بر آیند و مغرب فرو روند بی شک خدا در مشرق <lb/> باشد گفتند بلی گفت پس اولی آن باشد که در نماز روی سوی مشرق کنیم آن گروه از بیت <lb/> المقدس روی بر گردانیدند و نماز سوی مشرق کردند بعد از مدتی گروهی دیگر را بخواند و گفت <lb/> حق تعالی همه چیز را نه از بهر منفعت آدمی آفریده است گفتند بلی گفت چرا باید که گوشت گاو <lb/> حلال باشد و گوشت خوک حرام من چنان بینم که گوشت خوک حلال است آن گروه گوشت خوک <lb/> بر خود حلال کردند بعد از مدتی جمعی دیگر را بطلبید و گفت زنده کردن و آفریدن جز خدای <lb/> تعالی دیگری را میسر نشود گفتند نه گفت پس عیسی باید که خدا باشد که او مرغ آفرید و مرده</p>
                     <p>و مرغ</p>
                     <p>زنده کرد بعد از مدتی خلق را جمع کرد و گفت دوش عیسی را بخواب دیدم گفت اکنون از تو <lb/> راضی شدم و دست بر روی من نهاد حق از برکت دست او چشم مرا روشن کرد و مرا سخنی چند <lb/> گفت که با شما بگویم از علما و بزرگان خود جمعی را اختیار کرده حاضر کنید تا پیغام بگزارم ایشان <lb/> مرد از اکابر علماء خود پیش گفتند او حاضر کردند گفت يك يك پيش من در آیند اول یکی را <lb/> طلب داشت و او را گفت عیسی مرا گفت چرا مرا بنده خوانند و شما دایند که من مرده زنده کرده ام <lb/> آفریده و کور مادرزاد را بینا کردم و اینها جز خدا نتواند کردن من خدا ام باید که مرا <lb/> خدا خوانید آن مرد قبول کرد که چنین گوید و از پیش او بیرون آمد پس آن دیگر را طلب <lb/> داشت و او را گفت عیسی مرا گفت که امّت مرا بگو که من چیزها كردم كه جز خدا نکند چرا مرا <lb/> بنده خدا خوایند من شريك خدا ام باید که در حق من این اعتقاد کنید آن مرد از و قبول کرد <lb/> و از پیش او بیرون آمد پس سدیگر را طلب داشت و گفت مرا عیسی گفت من پسر خداام و شما <lb/> دیدید و شنیدید که من چه آفریده و چگونه مرده زنده کردم باید که در انجیل همچنین خوانید <lb/> آن مرد از و قبول کرد و از پیش او بیرون آمد پس بولس هم آن شب خود را بکشت و بعضی <lb/> گویند بولس گفت چون پیغام او رسانیدم پیش او خواهم رفت و پیش خلق خود را بکشت روز دیگر <lb/> مردم چون آن حال بدیدند پیش ایشان هر سه رفتند و گفتند بولس پیغام عیسی بشما چه رسانید هر <lb/> کس گفتند دیگر دیگر را خلاف کردند و اختلاف میان ایشان بر خاست و بعضی گویند بولس هر <lb/> سه را گفت که عیسی مرا گفت که من پسر خدا ام پس هر سه خلاف کردند که این چگونه باشد <lb/> و اختلاف بدین سبب میان ایشان واقع شد و نام ایشان یکی نسطور بود و یکی ملکا و <lb/> دیگری <lb/> مار يعقوب و چون مقالات ایشان طولی دارد و در این چندان فایده نیست در آن شروعی نرفت</p>
                     <p>This fine old MS., bought of the late IIájjí 'Abdu'l-Majid Belshah in January, <lb/> 1920, comprises 216 ff. of 28 x 20'5 c. and 23 ll., is written in a large, clear, archaic <lb/> naskh with rubrications, and is dated the 5th of Dhu'l-Qa'da, 731/August 10, 1330.</p>
                  </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="J_21-item1">
                     <author key="person_56411441" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/56411441/">
                        <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" type="standard">Tustarī, Muḥammad ibn Asʻad ibn ʻAbd Allāh al-Ḥanafī</persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">محمد بن اسعد بن عبد الله <addName xml:lang="ar" type="laqab">الحنفي</addName>
                           <addName xml:lang="ar" type="nisbah">التستري</addName>
                        </persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc" key="work_20856" change="#ids-cleanup">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyāʼ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="fa" key="work_20856" change="#ids-cleanup">قصص الانبياء</title>
                     <incipit xml:lang="ar"/>
                     <explicit xml:lang="ar" defective="true"/>
                     <note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar"/>
                     </note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                           <ref target="https://cudl.lib.cam.ac.uk/view/PR-A-00233-00004/165">p.139</ref>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl type="text-relations">This work is a Persian version of the Arabic <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Qiṣaṣ al-Qurʼān al-Karīm <foreign xml:lang="ar">قصص القرآن الكريم</foreign>
                           </title> of <author key="person_12069464"
                                   ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12069464/"
                                   role="ant"
                                   change="#role-assignment">
                              <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Būshanjī, al-Hayṣam ibn Muḥammad, 11th cent.</persName>
                              <persName xml:lang="ar">بوشنجي، الهيصم بن محمد</persName>
                           </author>.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="fa">Persian</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc change="#ai-catalogue">
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <support>Paper</support>
                        <extent>Ff. 216
                                    <dimensions unit="cm">
                              <height>28</height>
                              <width>20.5</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout>
                           <p>23 lines</p>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="naskh">Large, clear, archaic naskh with rubrications</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin change="#fix-dates">
                     <origDate notBefore="1330" notAfter="1331" calendar="#Hijri-qamari">731</origDate>
                     <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" when="1330">1330</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <p>This fine old MS., bought of the late <persName key="person_f7815" role="fmo">ájjí 'Abdu'l-Majid Belshah</persName>H in January, 1920.</p>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bequest of <persName xml:lang="en"
                               type="standard"
                               key="person_29651479"
                               ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29651479/"
                               role="fmo"
                               change="#role-assignment">E. G. Browne</persName>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source> Summary, physical description and provenance copied from <ref target="https://cudl.lib.cam.ac.uk/view/PR-A-00233-00004/1">R. A.
            Nicholson: <hi rend="italic">A descriptive catalogue of the Oriental MSS belonging to the late E.G.
            Browne</hi>. Cambridge, 1932</ref>.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/cgi-bin/eligibility.cgi/">Cambridge University Library Admissions</ref>). Contact <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="local_class">
               <category xml:id="commentary"/>
               <category xml:id="supercommentary"/>
               <category xml:id="translation">
                  <catDesc>translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="multipleWorks"/>
               <category xml:id="abridgement"/>
               <category xml:id="papers"/>
               <category xml:id="documents"/>
               <category xml:id="extract"/>
               <category xml:id="gloss"/>
               <category xml:id="selection"/>
               <category xml:id="diagrams"/>
               <category xml:id="notes"/>
               <category xml:id="letters"/>
               <category xml:id="palimpsest"/>
               <category xml:id="supplement"/>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85107529"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85107529#concept">Prophets, Pre-Islamic</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85072995"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85072995#concept">Koran stories</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025" xml:id="check-ai"><persName>Syed Gillani</persName></change>
         <change when="2025-06-04" xml:id="ai-catalogue">Values generated from legacy catalogue using a combination of AI and manual editing.</change>
         <change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="role-assignment">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName> Assigned role(s) to every person having an id (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="ids-cleanup">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName> Changed person and work ids (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2018-06-08">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Updated key attributes using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/update-keys.xsl">update-keys.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-15" xml:id="add-summary">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Added summary using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/add-summaries.xsl">add-summaries.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-02" xml:id="fix-dates">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Added or modified attributes in origDate elements using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/fix-dates.xsl">fix-dates.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-08-10">
            <persName>Ignacio Sanchez</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
