<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_756">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>L. 4</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Near and Middle Eastern Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Cambridge University Library</addrLine>
                  <street>West Road</street>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <postCode>CB3 9DR</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/deptserv/neareastern/">Cambridge University Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">L_4</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="L_4" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Cambridgeshire</region>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution>Cambridge University</institution>
                  <repository>University Library</repository>
                  <collection>E. G. Browne Collection</collection>
                  <idno>L. 4</idno>
                  <altIdentifier change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <idno>L. 4 (9), L. 5 (9)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <p>Two volumes of fictitious letters about the ancient glories and present misery <lb/>
                                of Persia, supposed to have been written by an imaginary Prince of India named <lb/>
                                Kamálu'd-Dawla to an equally imaginary Prince of Persia named Jalálu'd-Dawla, <lb/>
                                but really composed by Mírzá Áqá Khán of Kirmán, who was secretly put to death <lb/>
                                at Tabriz with Shaykh Ahmad Rúbí of Kirmán and the Khabiru'l-Mulk on July <lb/>
                                15, 1896. See Colonel D. C. Phillott's English Introduction to the Persian transla- <lb/>
                                tion of Morier's Haji Baba (Calcutta, 1905, pp. vii-viii), and my Persian <lb/>
                                Revolution, pp. 93–96.</p>
                     <p>Both these volumes were transcribed for me in A.D. 1911 by the Bábí scribe <lb/>
                                Mirza Mustafà, who supplied me with so many Bábí MSS. They are uniform in <lb/>
                                size (21'8 x 14'5 c. and 18 ll.) and script (a clear but not very graceful naskh), and <lb/>
                                were received by me together in October, 1912.</p>
                     <p>L. 4 comprises 160 ff., and is incomplete, for of the hundred letters or addresses <lb/>
                                (khilala) to Jalalu'd-Din which it should contain it actually contains only forty-two,</p>
                     <p>It is headed:</p>
                     <p>بنام ایزد یکتا</p>
                     <p>صورت یکصد خطابه است که شاهزاده آزاده كمال الدوله دهلوی که پدرش در زمان شاه تیمور از <lb/>
                                ایران بمرز و بوم هندوستان هجرت کرده بدوست محترم خود نواب جلال الدوله شاهزاده ایران <lb/>
                                نوشته است و شرح خرابی آنرا نگاشته</p>
                     <p>The imaginary writer, Kamálu'd-Dawla, begins by expressing his regret that, <lb/>
                                contrary to the advice of his friend Jalálu'd-Dawla, he returned from his travels in <lb/>
                                Europe to India by way of Persia, the condition of which caused him the deepest</p>
                     <p>mortification:</p>
                     <p>خطابه اوّل دوست عزیز من جلال الدوله عاقبت سخن ترا نشنیده در مراجعت از فرنگستان از راه <lb/>
                                تبریز وارد بخاک اندوهناك ایران شدم ایکاش نیآمده و هموطنان قدیم و خویشان کهن و وطن <lb/>
                                اصلی پر بلا و محن خود را ندیده بودم و از احوال و عادات و اخلاق و روش و کیش و مذهب <lb/>
                                و آئین ایشان مطلع ،نمیگشتم دلم خون و آب و جگرم پارچه پارچه و کباب شد</p>
                     <p>The leading motive of the book is the glorification of ancient and the disparage- <lb/>
                                ment of modern Persia. The Arabs are denounced as barbarians, and Islám, <lb/>
                                especially the Shí'a doctrine, is sharply criticized, while not only Zoroaster but even <lb/>
                                the communist Mazdak (f. 65') is applauded. The author makes a great display of <lb/>
                                his knowledge of European, especially French, words, and constantly puts forward <lb/>
                                the most absurd popular etymologies. Thus he detects the Persian word núr or <lb/>
                                khar (sun) in such place names as Europe, Urús (Russia), Urúm (Rúm, Asia <lb/>
                                Minor), Arman (Armenia), and Arnawd (Albania), and deduces from this a Persian <lb/>
                                origin or suzerainty for all these people. He derives Khidiw (Khedive) from <lb/>
                                Mahádíw; Astronomy from Sitára-náma; Mábadán from Mah-ábádiyán (a mythical <lb/>
                                ancient dynasty of Persian kings mentioned in the spurious Dasátír); 'Ibrání <lb/>
                                (Hebrew) from 'abara, "to cross over," because they crossed over the Euphrates to <lb/>
                                go into Egypt. He praises the open antagonism to Islám of the Carmathians, <lb/>
                                Ismá flís and Assassins (ff. 86-88), but condemns the later 'ulamá, philosophers, <lb/>
                                and heresiarchs of Persia, including Mullá Sadrá, Shaykh Murtada, Shaykh Ahmad <lb/>
                                al-Aḥsá'í and the Báb, whose ignorance, he says (f. 53'), is such that "not one of <lb/>
                                them has hitherto uttered two words calculated to benefit Persia," while the Súffs <lb/>
                                and mystics are also held up to contempt (f. 95), as well as poets like Qa'áni. <lb/>
                                Polygamy is condemned, the miserable position of Persian women deplored, and</p>
                     <p>the Persian character disparaged to such a point that the author says (f. 139) that <lb/>
                                though, except the Arabs and savages of Africa, there are no people more filthy and <lb/>
                                unclean than the Persians, the Jews resident in Persia, and the Hindús, these are <lb/>
                                the very people who regard everyone else as unclean. The evil effects of the <lb/>
                                rawda-khwáns and Muharram mournings, especially on women and their unborn <lb/>
                                offspring, are also emphasised. These rawa-kwáns, says the author (f. 155"). <lb/>
                                ought to be publicly flayed alive as a warning to others:</p>
                     <p>حق روضه خوان این است که او را زنده در ملاء عام پوست کنند و عبرت دیگران سازند تا دیگر <lb/>
                                کسی بندگان خدارا باین جرئت دعوت بر هدم ارکان شریعت و خرق پرده دیانت ننماید کمان <lb/>
                                ندارم آنقدر ظلمیکه بر اولاد و احفاد و جنینهای رحم زنان ایران و نطفهای کمر مردان از روضه <lb/>
                                خوانان میشود از فرعون که هزاران طفل سر بریده شده باشد زیراکه ما از پیش نوشتیم که حالات <lb/>
                                البته خو و طبیعت اصلی میشود <lb/>
                                عارضی مادران در اطفال رحم</p>
                     <p>L. 5, the companion volume, comprises 170 ff., and is described as containing <lb/>
                                three letters from the same Indian Prince Kamálu'd-Dawla to his Persian friend <lb/>
                                Jalálu'd-Dawla, but only the title of the first letter, supposed to have been written <lb/>
                                from Tabriz in Ramadán, 1282/Jan.-Feb., 1866, appears (on f. 8") in the text. <lb/>
                                The book begins:</p>
                     <p>هو الله تعالى</p>
                     <p>تا خوابت نکند صحبت رندانی چند <lb/>
                                زاهد از کوچه رندان بسلامت بگذر <lb/>
                                صورت سه طغرا مکتوبی است که شاهزاده آزاده کمال الدوله هندوستانی در جواب جلال الدوله <lb/>
                                ایرانی مرقوم داشته</p>
                     <p>The writer begins by explaining some score of European words and expressions <lb/>
                                which, he says, cannot be properly rendered in Persian, and which he therefore <lb/>
                                proposes to use in the course of his book. These include the words Despot, <lb/>
                                Civilization, Fanatic, Philosopher, Revolution, Progress, Poetry (Poésie), Patriot, <lb/>
                                Change (Changement), Politics, Protestant, Free (Libre), Electric, Charlatan, <lb/>
                                Parliament, Petrarch, Voltaire, Chemistry (Chimie), etc. The contents of this <lb/>
                                volume closely resemble the preceding one; the same abuse of the Arabs; the same <lb/>
                                absurd popular etymologies (Shaytan derived from Scythian; the magical word <lb/>
                                badúḥ, written on letters to ensure their arrival, from bi-daw, "run," etc.); the <lb/>
                                same condemnation of the 'ulamá, especially the Shi'a 'ulamá, of Islám; the same <lb/>
                                glorification of Zoroastrianism and pre-Islamic Persia; and the same denunciations <lb/>
                                of her later theologians, philosophers, darwishes and rawḍa-khwáns. Some account <lb/>
                                of the great persecution of the Bábís in the summer of A.D. 1852 is given on <lb/>
                                ff. 109-115. An imaginary dialogue between a tyrannical governor entitled <lb/>
                                Súsmáru d-Dawla ("the Lizard of the State") and the Kalántar occupies ff. 120- <lb/>
                                155, while almost at the end of the book an attempt is made to prove on etymo- <lb/>
                                logical grounds (jeune jwain; mort-murd; père-pidar; porté-burda; apporté</p>
                     <p>= áwurda; entrez = andar á; dent = dindán; lèvre=lab; genou=zánú; ville=bi <lb/>
                                in Ardabil, etc.) the close affinity between the French and the Persians.</p>
                     <p>Perhaps the most interesting passage in either of these depressing volumes is <lb/>
                                an account of an observance of the Zoroastrians of Yazd and Kirmán entitled <lb/>
                                Sufra-sabzi and "the entertainment of the Daughter of the King of the Fairies" <lb/>
                                (L. 4, ff. 20-22b).</p>
                     <p>The transcription of L. 5 was completed on the 8th of Dhu'l-Hijja, 1329 (Nov. <lb/>
                                30, 1911).</p>
                  </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="L_4-item1" class="#letters">
                     <note>Vol. 1</note>
                     <author key="person_79145663030605070860"
                             ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79145663030605070860/"
                             change="#ids-cleanup">
                        <persName xml:lang="en" type="standard">Āqā Khān Kirmānī, ʻAbd al-Husayn, 1854-1896 or 7</persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">آقا خان کرمانى، عبد الحسين</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="desc" key="work_20">Ficticious letters about the ancient glories and present misery of Persia</title>
                     <incipit xml:lang="ar"/>
                     <explicit xml:lang="ar" defective="true"/>
                     <note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar"/>
                     </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="fa">Persian</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc change="#ai-catalogue">
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <support>Paper</support>
                        <extent>Ff. 160 and 170
                                    <dimensions unit="cm">
                              <height>21.8</height>
                              <width>14.5</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout>
                           <p>18 lines</p>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote>A clear but not very graceful naskh script</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin change="#fix-dates">
                     <origDate notBefore="1910" notAfter="1911" calendar="#Hijri-qamari">1329</origDate>
                     <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" when="1911">1911</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <p>Received in October, 1912</p>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bequest of <persName xml:lang="en"
                               type="standard"
                               key="person_29651479"
                               ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29651479/"
                               role="fmo"
                               change="#role-assignment">E. G. Browne</persName>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source> Summary, physical description and provenance copied from <ref target="https://cudl.lib.cam.ac.uk/view/PR-A-00233-00004/1">R. A.
            Nicholson: <hi rend="italic">A descriptive catalogue of the Oriental MSS belonging to the late E.G.
            Browne</hi>. Cambridge, 1932</ref>.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/cgi-bin/eligibility.cgi/">Cambridge University Library Admissions</ref>). Contact <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl type="related">Work in two volumes bearing the class-marks: <idno>L. 4</idno> and <idno>L. 5</idno>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="local_class">
               <category xml:id="commentary"/>
               <category xml:id="supercommentary"/>
               <category xml:id="translation"/>
               <category xml:id="multipleWorks"/>
               <category xml:id="abridgement"/>
               <category xml:id="papers"/>
               <category xml:id="documents"/>
               <category xml:id="extract"/>
               <category xml:id="gloss"/>
               <category xml:id="selection"/>
               <category xml:id="diagrams"/>
               <category xml:id="notes"/>
               <category xml:id="letters">
                  <catDesc>letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="palimpsest"/>
               <category xml:id="supplement"/>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85100074"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85100074#concept">Persian letters</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85064462"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85064462#concept">Imaginary letters</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-06-04" xml:id="ai-catalogue">Values generated from legacy catalogue using a combination of AI and manual editing.</change>
         <change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="role-assignment">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName> Assigned role(s) to every person having an id (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="ids-cleanup">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName> Changed person and work ids (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2018-06-08">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Updated key attributes using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/update-keys.xsl">update-keys.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-02" xml:id="fix-dates">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Added or modified attributes in origDate elements using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/fix-dates.xsl">fix-dates.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-08-11">
            <persName>Ignacio Sanchez</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
