<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tei-for-special-collections/consolidated-schema/refs/heads/main/releases/rng/manuscripts-catalogue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1880">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>O. 1</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Cambridge University Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Near and Middle Eastern Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Cambridge University Library</addrLine>
                  <street>West Road</street>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <postCode>CB3 9DR</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/deptserv/neareastern/">Cambridge University Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">O_1</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="O_1" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Cambridgeshire</region>
                  <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
                  <institution>Cambridge University</institution>
                  <repository>University Library</repository>
                  <collection>E. G. Browne Collection</collection>
                  <idno>O. 1</idno>
                  <altIdentifier change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <idno>O. 1 (10)</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary change="#ai-catalogue">
                     <p>المفرد</p>
                     <p>ليط</p>
                     <p>A very fine and rare old Persian manuscript of Astronomical Tables, Chronology <lb/>and Eras, entitled Ziju'l-Mufrad, by Abú Ja'far Muhammad ibn Ayyub al-Hasib <lb/>at-Tabari, who flourished in the early part of the thirteenth century of the Christian <lb/>era. No other copy is known to exist, but a fragment of 26 pages preserved at <lb/>Munich may possibly be from this MS., which is incomplete at the end. It appears <lb/>to have been copied during the author's life-time by or for a certain Yusuf ibn <lb/>Abí..., but is not dated.</p>
                     <p>Begins, after the Bismi'lláh and short doxology:</p>
                     <p>بعد ثنای ایزد سبحانه و تعالی که آفریدگار دو جهان و روزی ده بندگانست و پروردگار جانورانست <lb/>و کردگار آسمانها و زمینهاست و دارنده هرج در میانشانست و درودش بر خاتم پیغمبران علیهم <lb/>السلم و بر جمله یارانش و گزیدگانش چنین گوید محمد بن ايوب الحاسب الطبري کي چون <lb/>بپرداخته بودم از عمل نخستین عملی زیج مفرد آغاز کردم بابتدا کردن مقاله دوم که اورا مقاله <lb/>علمی خواندم و اندرو پدید کردم هر علمی را که اندر مقاله نخستین بجدول ياذ كرده بودم <lb/>و بنموده اندرین مقاله جمله را بحساب نمودیم و آنج ازین دانش است نیز تمامی (?) بنمودیم از</p>
                     <p>حساب و عمل و علم و هیئه و برهان چنانک در مقاله نخستین وعده داده و پذیرفته بودم و این <lb/>مقالت را دو فصل نهاذم فصل نخستین در حساب و عمل و فصل دوم در هئات و برهان و از ایزد <lb/>سبحانه و تعالی توفیق خواستم بر تمام شدن هريك كى او توانا است بر آنك توفیق دهد</p>
                     <p>The work comprises four sections (Fasl), each containing many subsections, and <lb/>a Kitábu'l-Istikhráját (ff. 100-180'), consisting almost entirely of astronomical <lb/>tables. There are no catch-words at the foot of the pages, and some lacunae and <lb/>dislocations certainly exist, e.g. between ff. I and 2.</p>
                     <p>Section I (ff. 1-38) contains 77 subsections. <lb/>Section II (ff. 39"-60") contains 23 subsections. <lb/>Section III (ff. 60-76") contains 30 subsections. <lb/>Section IV (ff. 77-99) contains 45 subsections.</p>
                     <p>The first nineteen chapters of Section I deal with the years and festivals of the <lb/>Arabs, Persians, Jews and Christians (Greeks), as follows:</p>
                     <p>الاول در مدخل سنون العرب الثانى در مدخل سنون الفرس، الثالث در مدخل سنون اليهود <lb/>الرابع در مدخل سنون الروم الخامس در معرفة كبيسة العرب السادس در معرفة كبيسة سنون <lb/>الفرس السابع، در معرفة سنون كبيسة اليهود الثامن در شناختن سالهای کبیسه روم، التاسع، در <lb/>بیرون آوردن روزها از سالهای رومی ،العاشر در بیرون آوردن سالها و ماههای رومی از روزها، الحادی <lb/>عشر، در بیرون آوردن روزها از سالها و ماههای یهود الثانی عشر در بیرون آوردن سالها و ماههای</p>
                     <p>یهود از روزها الثالث عشر در بیرون آوردن روزها از سالها و ماههای عرب الرابع عشر، در بیرون <lb/>آوردن سالها و ماههای پارسی از روزها الخامس عشر در بیرون آوردن روزها از سال و ماه پارسی <lb/>السادس عشر، در بیرون آوردن سال و ماه پارسی از روزها السابع عشر در استخراج تاریخی مجهول <lb/>از تاریخی معلوم الثامن عشر در استخراج صوم ،نصاری التاسع عشر، در معرفة توقيعات و اعياد</p>
                     <p>Most of these chapters are very short, the 19 enumerated above being all</p>
                     <p>included in 8 ff.</p>
                     <p>The following titles, some entirely in red, some partly in red and partly in black, <lb/>stand at the heads of the different sections:</p>
                     <p>الـ</p>
                     <p>على</p>
                     <p>و</p>
                     <p>الفصل الاول من مقالة العلمية من كتاب زيج المفرد تصنيف الشيخ الجليل الاوحد ابى جعفر <lb/>محمد بن ايوب الحاسب الطبرى ادام الله تمكنه صاحبه ومالكه يوسف بن ابی ... طول الله عمره</p>
                     <p>(f. 1a)</p>
                     <p>الفصل الثاني من مقالة العملية من كتاب زيج المفرد تصنيف الشيخ الجليل الاوحد ابى جعفر <lb/>محمد بن ايوب الحاسب الطبرى ادام الله تمکینه صاحبه ومالكه يوسف بن ... طول الله عمره</p>
                     <p>(f. 39°)</p>
                     <p>فصل سیم از مقاله عملی (f. 6o)</p>
                     <p>فصل چهارم از مقاله عملی صاحبه و مالكه يوسف بن ... متعه الله عمره ، (77 .f)</p>
                     <p>The owner's name recurs in the corner of this page with the date 700/1300-1 <lb/>(as in Section 11).</p>
                     <p>كتاب الاستخراجات (100 .f) تصنيف الشيخ الجليل الخ</p>
                     <p>I cannot decipher the name of the father of the owner Yusuf satisfactorily in <lb/>any one of the four places where it occurs, though it is mutilated only in the first, <lb/>where it appears to be. In the others it looks like J, with only the one <lb/>diacritical point and a puzzling ligature of the first three or four letters.</p>
                     <p>On f. 108 occurs a circular figure indicating the appearances of the new moons, <lb/>ascribed to Abú Rayhán [ie. al-Birúni, to whom the title ash-Shaykhu'r Ra's, <lb/>commonly applied to Avicenna, is given, as follows:</p>
                     <p>دايرة روية الاهلة من عمل الشيخ الرئيس الحكيم برهان الحق أبي ربحان رحمه الله تعالى</p>
                     <p>This MS., bought of the late Hajji 'Abdu'l-Majid Belshah in January, 1920, <lb/>comprises 180 ff. of 24'2 x 16'2 c. and 21 ll., and is written for the most part in a <lb/>beautiful archaic naskh, with rubrications, though some pages (e.g. ff. 39-59") are <lb/>in a poorer and cruder, though quite legible, hand.</p>
                  </summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="O_1-item1">
                     <author key="person_76204439" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/76204439/">
                        <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" type="standard">Ṭabarī, Muḥammad ibn Ayyūb, 11th cent.</persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">طبرى، محمد بن ايوب <addName xml:lang="ar" type="laqab">الحاسب</addName>
                           <addName xml:lang="ar" type="kunyah">ابو جعفر</addName>
                        </persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" key="work_1782">Zīj al-mufrad</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar" key="work_1782">زيج المفرد</title>
                     <incipit xml:lang="ar"/>
                     <explicit xml:lang="ar" defective="true"/>
                     <note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar"/>
                     </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="fa">Persian</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc change="#ai-catalogue">
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <support>Paper</support>
                        <extent>Ff. 180<dimensions unit="cm">
                              <height>24.2</height>
                              <width>16.2</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout>
                           <p>21 lines</p>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="naskh">A beautiful archaic naskh, with rubrications, though some pages are in a poorer and cruder, though quite legible, hand.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin change="#fix-dates">undated</origin>
                  <provenance change="#ai-catalogue">Bought of the late <persName key="person_f7815" role="fmo">Hajji 'Abdu'l-Majid Belshah</persName> in January, 1920.</provenance>
                  <acquisition>Bequest of <persName xml:lang="en"
                               type="standard"
                               key="person_29651479"
                               ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/29651479/"
                               role="fmo"
                               change="#role-assignment">E. G. Browne</persName>.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source> Summary, physical description and provenance copied from <ref target="https://cudl.lib.cam.ac.uk/view/PR-A-00233-00004/1">R. A.
            Nicholson: <hi rend="italic">A descriptive catalogue of the Oriental MSS belonging to the late E.G.
            Browne</hi>. Cambridge, 1932</ref>.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/cgi-bin/eligibility.cgi/">Cambridge University Library Admissions</ref>). Contact <email>near_eastern@lib.cam.ac.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85009022"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85009022#concept">Astronomy, Medieval</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85025414"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85025414#concept">Islamic chronology</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85112615"
                           target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85112615#concept">Religious calendars</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025" xml:id="check-ai"><persName>Syed Gillani</persName></change>
         <change when="2025-06-04" xml:id="ai-catalogue">Values generated from legacy catalogue using a combination of AI and manual editing.</change>
         <change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="role-assignment">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName> Assigned role(s) to every person having an id (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2018-06-08">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Updated key attributes using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/update-keys.xsl">update-keys.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-15" xml:id="add-summary">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Added summary using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/add-summaries.xsl">add-summaries.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2018-03-02" xml:id="fix-dates">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Removed origDate tags around something which is not a date using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/fix-dates.xsl">fix-dates.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-08-11">
            <persName>Ignacio Sanchez</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
