<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/bodley-msDesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/bodley-msDesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1002">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>OXFORD AND CAMBRIDGE ISLAMIC MANUSCRIPTS CATALOGUE ONLINE</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bodleian Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Special Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bodleian Library</addrLine>
                  <street>Broad Street</street>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/libraries/collections">Bodleian Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>oriental@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Huntington_359</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Huntington_359" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>Oxford University</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection type="main">Oriental Manuscripts Huntington Collection</collection>
                  <idno>MS. Huntington 359</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#multipleWorks">
                  <summary>The volume contains 131 leaves. Folio 30b has an eleven-line Turkish note, carefully written, on the treatment of haemorrhoids (بواسير). Folio 31a has twenty lines of Arabic in a large later hand concerned with the meaning of terms used in describing temperaments and humours. Folio 131a has advice (من وصايا) on food (طعام) taken from Ibn Sīnā, written in a large and later hand. Folio 131b has four recipes for theriacs (in different hands), one of them specified as ترياق برشعيثا (the tiryāq of Barashʿīthā) and another as ترياق فاروق لابن قيسون (the tiryāq fārūq of Ibn Qaysūn). Surrounding the title on folio 1a there are later notes presenting three magical procedures for gaining protection and well-being, one of them citing Sulaymān ibn Dāwūd (King Solomon son of David). On the front pastedown, in addition to the UAM entry number, there are Turkish recipes, medical notes and pious phrases; on the back pastedown there are two recipes, one for skin conditions and leprosy (judhām). On the paper lining of the envelope flap there are four invocations (yā kāfī, etc.) that are said, on the authority of al-Būnī (d. c. 622/1225), to be useful for procuring a livelihood and wealth. A Latin note on folio 1b states that the volume contains commentaries on the Aphorisms of Hippocrates.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Huntington_359-item1" n="1" class="#abridgement">
                     <locus from="1" to="30">ff. 1v-30r</locus>
                     <author key="person_44299175" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/44299175">
                        <persName type="standard">Galen,<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="0216">d. c. 216</date>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">جالينوس</persName>
                     </author>
                     <editor role="abridger">
                        <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Nīlī, Abū Sahl Saʻīd ibn ʻAbd al-ʻAzīz, 964 - 1029</persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">ابو سهل سعيد بن عبد العزيز النيلى</persName>
                     </editor>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Talkhīṣ tafsīr Jālīnūs li-Fuṣūl Ibqurāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt">An Abridgement of the Commentary by Galen on the Aphorisms of Hippocrates</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar"> تلخيص تفسير جالينوس لفصول إبقراط</title>
                     <incipit>بسم الله ... قال الشيخ ابو سهل سعيد بن عبد العزيز النيلى رحمه الله ان الذى دعانى[غير معجمة] الى تلخيص تفسير جالينوس لفصول ابقراط مع قصور الوسع والاقرار عن الاتيان بمثل من النظم فى الحسن والبيان ما رائيت [= رأيت] من تكاسل الاصحاب عن النظر[غير معجمة] فى الكتب الطويل</incipit>
                     <explicit>قال بقراط من كان لحمه رطبا فينبغي ان يجوع فان الجوع يجفف الابدان ص [= تلخيص] تجفيف الجوع بطريق العرض وذلك انه حتى لم يكن يدل المتحلل خلف ((جف صح)) العضو لان اول ما يتحلل ک من كل عضو ارطب ما فيه ﻫ . تم [= ثم] قال وما يلى هذه الفصول من الكتاب اما مدلسه او معاد قد سبق شرحها</explicit>
                     <colophon>تم الكتاب بعون الملك الوهاب فى شهر صفر لسنة اربع وعشرين وتسعمائة</colophon>
                     <note>Ibn Abī Uṣaibiʻah I. 453-4, who mentions this work</note>
                     <note>It was transcribed in the month of Ṣafar 924 (12 Feb.–12 Mar. 1518) by an unnamed copyist. The copy is incomplete. The first maqālah begins on folio 1b and the second on folio 6a, but the second maqālah ends abruptly on folio 10b16 at the fortieth aphorism, with no commentary. The text then continues in the middle of the third maqālah with the commentary on the twenty-second aphorism. The fourth maqālah begins on folio 12b, the fifth on 15b, the sixth on 21a, and the seventh on 26a. The seventh maqālah ends with the aphorism before the last one in that chapter − that is, it ends with the fifty-eighth aphorism of the last maqālah in the edition by John Tytler, The Aphorisms of Hippocrates, Translated into Arabic by Honain ben Ishak, physician to the Caliph Motawukkul (Calcutta: Education Press, 1832).</note>
                     <note>Dimensions 21.8 × 15.4 (text area 16.3 × 9.8) cm; 19 lines per page. The title and the name of the commentator, Galen, and the editor, al-Nīlī, occur at the beginning of the treatise and on the title page (folio 1a) which reads: هذا من الطب فى تلخيص تفسير جالينوس لفصول ابقراط شرح فصول ابقراط للشيخ الفاضل ابى سهل سعيد بن عبد العزيز النيلي رحمة الله عليه برحمته الواسعة The text area has been frame-ruled. The text is written in a medium-small, fairly casual and inelegant, but consistent, Naskh, not fully dotted and employing some ligatures; it is written in black ink with headings in black and black overlinings. There are catchwords. On the lower half of folio 23b the handwriting changes and then returns to the original hand on folio 24a; there is no catchword on folio 23b. It is soiled with thumbing on folios 2a−3a, 7a, and 11a.</note>
                     <note>The text has been collated (collation notes folio 11a, 11b, 15b, 16b, 21a, 21b, 22b, 24a, 24b, 25b, 26a, 27b, 28a, 30a). There are marginal corrections and marginal indications of chapters; on folio 4b there are pious phrases in the margin written by a later hand.</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>NCAM-1, Entry No. 2</bibl>
                        <bibl>NPAE, pp. 588−9</bibl>
                        <bibl>Appendix Medicine</bibl>
                        <bibl>[UAM. 614 [i], with corr. Nic. pp. 588, 589; revd. by Beeston]</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Huntington_359-item2" n="2" class="#commentary">
                     <locus from="31" to="130">ff. 31v-130v</locus>
                     <author key="person_4405945" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/4405945/">
                        <persName type="standard" xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Ibn Abī Ṣādiq al-Nīsābūrī, Abū al-Qāsim ʻAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʻAlī,<date calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1068">d. after 1068</date>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">ابو القاسم ععبد الرحمن بن علي بن ابي صادق النيسابوري‏</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Sharḥ Fuṣūl Ibqurāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt">Commentary on the Aphorisms of Hippocrates</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar">كتاب شرح فصول إبقراط</title>
                     <incipit>بسم الله ... قال الشيخ ابو القسم عبد الرحمن بن على بن ابى صادق رضى الله عنه بعد حمد الله بجميع محامده والثنا عليه بما هو اهله والصلوة على رسوله محمد النبى وآله وسلم ان العنايه التى تبعث الخلق[غير معجمة] على باب من ابواب العلوم من اشرف الفضايل الانسانية سيما ما كان الناس كافة امس حاجة اليه من غيره كعلم الطب علم الطب</incipit>
                     <explicit>واما الفصول المدلسه والتي قد اعيد ذكرها بآخره[غير معجمة] من الكتاب فتركنا ذكرها شفقة على فوت الزمان بما لا يجدى نفعا</explicit>
                     <colophon>تم الكتاب بعون الملك الوهاب فى اوآخر شهر شعبان لسنه اربع وعشرين وتسعمايه</colophon>
                     <note>The copy was completed toward the end of Shaʿbān 924<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1518">(Aug.–Sept. 1518)</date>. The unnamed copyist is the same person who copied the first item in the volume (see entry for Talkhīṣ tafsīr Jālīnūs li-Fuṣūl Ibqurāṭ ).</note>
                     <note>It is a nearly complete copy, with one small lacuna on folio 115a. The first maqālah begins on folio 32a, the second on 44b, the third on 56b, the fourth on 66a, the fifth on 86a, the sixth on 102b, and the seventh on 120a.</note>
                     <note>Dimensions 21.8 × 15.4 (text area 15.8 × 9.6) cm; 19 lines per page. The title is not given. The author is named at the beginning of the treatise.</note>
                     <note>The text area is frame-ruled. The text is written in a medium-small, fairly casual and inelegant, but consistent, Naskh, without full diacritical dots and employing some ligatures. It is written in dense-black ink; some black overlining was added later. There are catchwords.</note>
                     <note>The text has been collated, with collation notes throughout. Space has been left blank on folio 115a. There are also marginal corrections. Folio 31a has twenty lines in a large later hand concerned with the meaning of terms used in describing temperaments and humours. On folio 130b there is a later therapeutic note on phrenitis or meningitis (sirsām) and forgetfulness (nisyān).</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>NCAM-1, Entry No.3B</bibl>
                        <bibl>GAL I 484</bibl>
                        <bibl>UAM, 143 entry DCXIV (614); treatise and author are not mentioned</bibl>
                        <bibl>NPAE, 588−9</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <extent>
                           <ref target="#a1">30 ff.</ref>
                           <ref target="#a2">100 ff.</ref>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>
                        <label>Paper</label>The smooth, glossy, cream-beige paper has a thickness of 0.07–0.14 mm and an opaqueness factor of 8. It is unevenly fibrous, with vertical laid lines, single chain lines, and watermarks. The edges of the paper have been trimmed from their original size. Folio 131 is a different paper.</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <p>The volume is bound in pasteboard covers with envelope flap, covered with European marbled paper edged in brown leather. The envelope flap lining is yellow paper; the pastedowns on the covers incorporate older paper leaves. There are no endpapers. There are recent paper doublure hinges.</p>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <ref target="#a1">
                        <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" when="1518">1518</origDate>
                     </ref>
                     <ref target="#a2">
                        <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" when="1518">1518</origDate>
                     </ref>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>
                     <p>At the bottom of folio 1a there is an owner’s stamp (undated) and note, partially obliterated, transferring ownership in 1009 H<date calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1600" notAfter="1601">[1600−1]</date>to<persName>Efendi Muṣṭafá al-Zākarjī</persName>(?). The volume was in the collection of<persName>Robert Huntington</persName>, whose ex libris, with the numeral 95, is found on folio 1b.</p>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>It was purchased by the Bodleian Library in 1693 from Robert Huntington, together with the remainder of his collection of oriental manuscripts.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Manuscript description based on Emilie Savage-Smith; A New Catalogue of Arabic Manuscripts in The Bodleian Library, University of Oxford. Volume I: Medicine, Oxford: OUP, 2011.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card (for admissions procedures contact<ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/services/admissions/">Bodleian Admissions</ref>). Contact<email>oriental@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="local_class">
               <category xml:id="commentary">
                  <catDesc>Commentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supercommentary">
                  <catDesc>Supercommentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="indices">
                  <catDesc>Indices</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="translation">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="multipleWorks">
                  <catDesc>multipleWorks</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="abridgement">
                  <catDesc>Abridgement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supplement">
                  <catDesc>Supplement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="papers">
                  <catDesc>Papers</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="documents">
                  <catDesc>Documents</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="extract">
                  <catDesc>Extract</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="gloss">
                  <catDesc>Gloss</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="selection">
                  <catDesc>Selection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="diagrams">
                  <catDesc>Diagrams</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="notes">
                  <catDesc>Notes</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="letters">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="versification">
                  <catDesc>Versification</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="#a1 #a2">
                        <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85083064#concept">Medicine</ref>
                     </ref>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName>Up-converted the markup using<ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2014-02-14">
            <persName>Lydia Wright</persName>created this file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url="folio1r.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio1v.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio2r.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio2v.png"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
