<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1493">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>OXFORD AND CAMBRIDGE ISLAMIC MANUSCRIPTS CATALOGUE ONLINE</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bodleian Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Special Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bodleian Library</addrLine>
                  <street>Broad Street</street>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/libraries/collections">Bodleian Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Pococke_294</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Pococke_294" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>Oxford University</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection type="main">Oriental Manuscripts Pococke Collection</collection>
                  <idno>MS. Pococke 294</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>The volume contains 199 folios, with 3 preliminary leaves and 4 blank back leaves, all of later paper, as is folio 1 which is blank except for the aphorism: هذا كتاب لويباع بوزنه دهباً لكان البايع المغبون Even if this volume were sold for its weight in gold, the seller would have been cheated A small piece of paper removed at the time of rebinding is pasted onto folio 1, bearing a Latin note to the effect that it contains the commentary by Ibn al-Nafis (Ibn Naphîs Al Korashi) on the Hippocratic treatise on aphorisms.</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Pococke_294-item1">
                     <author key="person_17316331" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/17316331/">
                        <persName type="standard" xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Ibn al-Nafīs, ʻAlī ibn Abī al-Ḥazm, <date calendar="#Gregorian" from="1210" to="1288">1210 or 11-1288</date>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">ابن النفيس، علي بن أبي الحزم، ت. 687 هـ</persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" type="alt">Ibn al-Nafīs, ʻAlāʼ al-Dīn ʿAlī ibn Abī al-Ḥazm al-Qurashī (d. 687/1288)</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" key="work_20966" change="#ids-cleanup">Sharḥ al-Fuṣūl li-Ibqurāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar" key="work_20966" change="#ids-cleanup">شرح الفصول لإبقراط</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt" key="work_20966" change="#ids-cleanup">Commentary on the Aphorisms of Hippocrates</title>
                     <note>It is an incomplete copy containing only the first three maqālahs and about two-thirds of the fourth. It is stated in the colophon to be the first part (juzʼ ) only, suggesting that the copy originally comprised two fascicles. The second maqālah begins on folio 64a, the third on folio 119b (though it is mislabelled al-sābiʻah, ‘the seventh’), and the fourth on folio 168a. The Hippocratic text is usually introduced by qāla Ibqurāṭ and the commentary by al-sharḥ, written in red ink.</note>
                     <incipit xml:lang="ar">بسم الله … قال الشيخ الامام العالم العلامة وحيد دهره و فريد عصره على بن أبى الحزم [غير معجمة] القرشى المعروف بابن النفيس لكل زمان مقال والفاضل جالينوس قد شرح كتاب الفصول لامام هذه الصناعه ابقراط شرحاً كشف اسراره وأفاض علي ملتمسي هذا الفن انواره لكنه اعتمد على فطانه مشتغلي أهل زمانه في مواضع ظاهره فقصد فيها الاختصار وخصوصاً بيان ترتيب كل فصل في موضعه ومناسبته لما يحتف به فطن بعض من جآ بعده وعسر عليه فهمه ان ذلك لعدمه الترتيب حتى بالغ فى التحذلق قادجا فيه فقال انه عديم الضبط كثير الخبط فاحببت ان اكتب في ذلك من المباحث ما اظهر به محاسنه واثير دفاينه وأنا أسال الله المعونه على ذلك والتمس من الاصدقاء الذين من أهل المعرفة ان لا يبادروا فيما خالفت فيه المشهور بالنقص والابطال دون المراجعة والتأمل الخالي عن سوء الظن بالزمان واهله فالاعتبار بما قال لا بمن قال وقد جرت عادة الشراح ان يفتتحوا كُتب الشروح بتطويلات في مدح تلك الصناعة ومدح الكتاب الذي يشرح وقد رايت ان لا اضيع الزمان فيها. المقالة الاولي من كتاب الفصول لابقراط قال ابقراط العمر قصير والصناعة طويلة والوقت ضيق والتجربه خطر … الشرح العمر هو مدة بقاء النفس متصرفة في البدن وهو مدة الحياة والصناعة مَلَكَةٌ نفسانية يقتدر بها على استعمال</incipit>
                     <explicit xml:lang="ar">قال ابقراط مَن اعترته حُمَّي فأعوجت معها رقبته وعسر عليه الإزتارد [؟] حتى لا يقدر أن يزدرد الا بكدّ من غير ان يظهر به انتفاخ فذلك من علامات الموت الشرح لما اشتمل الفصل المتقدم على ذكر أحد أنواع الإختناق [؟] ((الردي)) الدال على الموت ذكر في هذا نوعاً اخر من تلك الانواع وهذا الإعوجاج[غير معجمة] قد يكون لاجل افراط اليبس المجفف … قال جالينوس ان عادة ابقراط اذا قال مثل هذا اراد به الحمى الشديده واما اذا اراد مطلق الحمى قال من كانت به حمى او ما يشبه ذلك قوله وليس في حلقه انتفاخ أي ورم لان ذلك ان كان عن اليبوسه فظاهر وان كان عن ورم فيكون كانه يقول وليس فى حلقه انتفاخ يظهر للحس</explicit>
                     <colophon xml:lang="ar">تم الجز الاول من شرح فصول ابقراط شرح الفقير الى الله علي زاني [= بن أبي] الحزم [غير معجمة] القرشي المتطبب يتلوه في الذي يليه قال ابقراط العرق يحمد في المحموم اذا ابتدا في اليوم الثالث او في اليوم الخامس ... أو في السابع ... وبالله التوفيق والمعونه</colophon>
                     <note>The copy is undated and unsigned. The appearance of the paper, ink, and script suggests a product of the seventh/thirteenth century. If the reading of the oldest owner’s note is correct, then the copy was made within the lifetime of the commentator, for the note appears to be dated 657 (1258−9) and signed by one ʿAlī ibn Abī Muḥammad ibn Maḥmūd al-ḥakīm al-Nābulusī. The general area of Nablus, where the owner was a physician, seems consistent with the likely place of production. The manuscript was certainly produced well before 880/1475−6, when a second owner’s note was entered.</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>NCAM-1, Entry No.6 A.</bibl>
                        <bibl>GAL I 493</bibl>
                        <bibl>[UAM. 544]</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <extent>198 ff. (folios 2b-199b) <dimensions type="leaf" unit="cm">
                              <height>26.4</height>
                              <width>18.1</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="cm">
                              <height>20.0</height>
                              <width>11.5</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <condition>
                           <p>The paper is water-stained and has some foxing towards the end; it is also soiled through thumbing (with fingerprints visible on folios 30b, 48a, 52a, and 147a). Folio 2 is guarded and the edges of folios 2 and 199 have been repaired.</p>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1" writtenLines="13" n="mistara">
                           <p>13 lines per page. The text area has been frame-ruled.</p>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote scope="major" script="naskh">
                        <desc>The text is written in a widely spaced, large, elegant, Naskh with occasional vocalization. The initial kāf is frequently missing the top stroke. The final letters of words at the end of a line are often written in the margin at a considerable distance from the ruled text area. The letters ḥāʼ and ʻayn have minuscule letters beneath, possibly added later, and the letter sīn occasionally has a háček. The text is written in black ink with headings in red.</desc>
                     </handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <label>Marginalia</label> The copy has been collated. At the bottom of folio 199b, alongside the colophon, in a hand slightly later than the copyist’s (using a brown ink) someone has written that it was collated from the beginning up to that point. Quires of ten leaves are numbered with Coptic numerals as well as Arabic numerals.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Paper</label> The smooth, semi-glossy beige paper has a thickness of 0.12–0.16 mm and an opaqueness factor of 5 to 6. It has horizontal laid lines and chain lines in groups of 3s.</item>
                     </list>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <p>The volume is bound in a nineteenth-century European library binding of tan leather over pasteboards; the covers have two blind-tooled simple frames. There are modern pastedowns and endpapers. The traces of an envelope flap from an earlier binding are visible on folio 1a.</p>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origPlace>Nablus?</origPlace>
                     <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1200" notAfter="1300" type="approxDate">Probably 13th Century</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>
                     <p>There are four notes on folio 2a. The oldest in appearance, written in faded brown ink, names the owner as ʻAlī ibn Abī Muḥammad ibn Maḥmūd al-ḥakīm al-Nābulusī (the last word has been reinked) and appears to be dated 657 (1258−9). Beneath that note, a somewhat later hand has written that it came into the possession of Nūr al-Dīn ibn ʻAlī al-ḥakīm and his brother ʻAbd al-Razzāq in the year 880 (1475−6); this same information, without the date, is repeated in a second note by a different hand. There are two additional undated notes, one of them rather illegible, though written with a calligraphic flourish, and the other defaced.</p>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>The volume is from the collection of Edward Pococke, which was mostly assembled in Aleppo in the 1630s and came into the Bodleian Library in 1692.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Manuscript description based on Emilie Savage-Smith; A New Catalogue of Arabic Manuscripts in The Bodleian Library, University of Oxford. Volume I: Medicine, Oxford: OUP, 2011</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card (for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/services/admissions/">Bodleian Admissions</ref>). Contact <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85083142" target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85083142#concept">Greek medicine</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh85083064" target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85083064#concept">Medicine</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
		<change when="2020-07-06" xml:id="ids-cleanup">
			<persName>Julian Cook</persName> Changed person and work ids (Fihrist data cleanup project).
		</change>
         <change when="2018-06-08">
            <persName>Andrew Morrison</persName> Updated key attributes using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/conversion_scripts/update-keys.xsl">update-keys.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2014-02-14">
            <persName>Lydia Wright</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url="folio1r.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio1v.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio2r.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio2v.png"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>