<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/bodley-msDesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/bodley-msDesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1797">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>OXFORD AND CAMBRIDGE ISLAMIC MANUSCRIPTS CATALOGUE ONLINE</title>
            <funder>JISC</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bodleian Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Special Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bodleian Library</addrLine>
                  <street>Broad Street</street>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/libraries/collections">Bodleian Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>oriental@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Thurston_10</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Thurston_10" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>Oxford University</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection type="main">Oriental Manuscripts Thurston Collection</collection>
                  <idno>MS. Thurston 10</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents class="#multipleWorks">
                  <summary>The volume contains 169 folios. Folio 118b has a table of contents written by a tenth/sixteenth-century hand for the second item in the volume. A table of contents for the first item is written by the same hand on the front pastedown, which also has a one-line Karshūnī note reading Kitāb Ibn Abī Ṣādiq, as well as Latin notes regarding the nature of the two main items in the volume, a Latin version of the opening of the first aphorism, and the date 20 March 1667. Folio 167a−b has a short discourse by one Nāṣir al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Jamāl al-Dīn Ibrāhīm ibn Sharaf al-Dīn Ismāʿīl ibn al-Ṭurays al-mutaṭabbib, written in a large and fairly early hand with many ligatures and very few dots, in which he says that the most noble of books on the medical arts is the Aphorisms of Hippocrates along with the Taqdimat al-maʿrifah (by al-Dakhwār, d. 628/1230), and that he immersed himself also in the Kitāb al-Nīlīyah by Abū Sahl ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz al-Nīlī (d. 420/1029) and the Kitāb al-Asbāb wa-al-ʿalāmāt of al-Samarqandī (d. 619/1222), amongst others. Folio 169ab is blank except for pagination in Arabic numerals. Karshūnī notes providing subject headings occur on folios 89a (al-ṣudāʿ, headache), 133a (fī al-istisqāʾ, on dropsy), 164a (fī al-buḥrānāt, on crises), and 165a (al-ruʿāf al-radī, a persistent nosebleed).</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Thurston_10-item1" n="1" class="#commentary">
                     <locus from="1" to="118">ff. 1-118</locus>
                     <author key="person_4405945" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/4405945/">
                        <persName type="standard" xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Ibn Abī Ṣādiq al-Nīsābūrī, Abū al-Qāsim ʻAbd al-Raḥmān ibn ʻAlī,<date calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1068">d. after 1068</date>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">ابو القاسم ععبد الرحمن بن علي بن ابي صادق النيسابوري‏</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Sharḥ Fuṣūl Ibqurāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt">Commentary on the<title>Aphorisms</title>of<persName type="standard"
                                  key="person_104252438"
                                  ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/104252438/">Hippocrates</persName>in the translation of<persName type="standard"
                                  xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc"
                                  key="person_19690624"
                                  ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/19690624/">Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq al-ʻIbādī,<date calendar="#Gregorian" from="0809" to="0873">809?-873</date>
                        </persName>
                     </title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar">كتاب شرح فصول إبقراط</title>
                     <incipit>بسم الله ... قال الشيخ الامام العالم ابو القسم [= القاسم] عبد الرحمن ابن على ابن ابى صادق رضى الله عنه  أما بعد حمد الله تعالى بجميع محامده والثنآ عليه بما هو اهله والصلوة على انبيآيه وسلم ان العنايه التى تبعث الخلق على افتيآ[= اقتناء] باب من ابواب الفضايل والعلوم لمن اشرف الفضايل الانسانية لا سيما ما كان الناس امس حاجة اليه من غيره كعلم الطب</incipit>
                     <explicit>واما الفصول المدلسه والتى قد اعيد ذكرها باخره من الكتاب فقد تركنا ذكرها شفقة عن فوت الزمان بما لا يجدى نفعا والله اعلم بالصواب واليه المرجع والمئاب [غير معجمة]. تم الكتاب بحمد الله ومنه وكرمه. الحمد لله وحده</explicit>
                     <note>The copy is undated and unsigned. It bears an owner’s note dated 761/<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1359">Gregorian</date>1359. The appearance of the paper, ink, and script suggest a dating of the seventh/thirteenth to eighth/fourteenth century.</note>
                     <note>It is a complete copy. The first maqālah begins on folio 2a, the second on 17b, the third on 34b, the fourth on 46a, the fifth on 67b, the sixth on 86a, and the seventh on 105b.</note>
                     <note>Dimensions 25.7 × 18.5 (text area 16.0 × 12.0) cm; 17−18 lines per page. The title is given on the title page (folio 1a) as كتاب فيه شرح فصول ابقراط; a later hand has repeated the title at the top of the page. The author’s name is given in full on both the title page and at the beginning of the treatise. The title is written as شرح الفصول on the top edge of the volume, with the author written as لابن ابى صادق on the bottom edge. The text area is frame-ruled. The text is written in a medium-small, careful, and consistent Naskh with considerable vocalization. The letter sīn and occasionally rāʾ has a small háček on it; a minuscule letter occurs underneath the letter ḥāʾ but only very occasionally under an ʿayn. The letter kāf often, but not always, is missing the top stroke; a hamzah is occasionally written over an initial alif. The text is written in dark brown ink, with headings and overlinings in red; text-stops are red dots enclosed in brown circles. There are no catchwords.</note>
                     <note>The text has been collated (collation note on folio 17b), and there are scribal corrections and later marginalia. Folios are labelled in the upper left corner with small abjad letter-numerals in black ink. A different hand has numbered the pages with standard Arabic numerals. On folio 89a there is a Karshūnī note providing the subject heading: al-ṣudāʿ (headache).</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>NCAM-1, Entry No.3A</bibl>
                        <bibl>GAL I 484</bibl>
                        <bibl>UAM, 129 entry DXXXIII (533), item 1</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Thurston_10-item2" n="2" class="#commentary">
                     <locus from="119" to="166">ff. 119v-166v</locus>
                     <author key="person_90045976" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/90045976/">
                        <persName type="standard" xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Muhadhdhab al-Dīn al-Dakhwār, ʻAbd al-Raḥīm ibn ʻAlī,<date calendar="#Gregorian" from="1169" to="1231">1169 or 70-1230 or 31</date>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">مهذب الدين الدخوار، عبد الرحيم علي، 565-628 هـ</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Sharḥ Kitāb Taqdimat al-maʿrifah li-Buqrāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar">شرح كتاب تقدمة المعرفة لبقراط</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt">Commentary on the<title>Prognostica</title>of<persName type="standard"
                                  key="person_104252438"
                                  ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/104252438/">Hippocrates</persName>in the translation of<persName type="standard"
                                  xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc"
                                  key="person_19690624"
                                  ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/19690624/">Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq al-ʻIbādī,<date calendar="#Gregorian" from="0809" to="0873">809?-873</date>
                        </persName>, ed by<persName xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" key="person_f601">Badr al-Dīn al-Muẓaffar ibn al-Qādī al-Baʻlabakkī<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1232">fl. c. 1232</date>
                        </persName>
                     </title>
                     <incipit>بسم الله ... يقول العبد الفقير الى رحمه ربّه الكريم الشيخ الامام العالم العامل الصدر الكبير الكامل الريس بدر الدين مظفر بن قاضى بعلبك الطبيب بلغه الله اماله فى الدنياء والاخره انني لمّا قرأت على الشيخ الامام العالم مهذب الدين عبد الرحمن ابن على الطبيب رحمه الله تعالى كتاب تقدمه المعرفه لبقراط اجتهد على غايه الاجتهاد من فرط اجتهادى</incipit>
                     <explicit>وكان قصده ايصال الراحه للمرضى بكل طريق فبذلك يحصل له حسن الثنآ من الناس والمجازاة من الله تعالى . تم الشرح وكمل بعون الله تعالى وحسن توفيقه نفع الله به كاتبه ومن طالعه امين رب العالمين وصلى الله على سيدنا محمد واله</explicit>
                     <note>This undated and unsigned copy is by the same copyist who prepared the first item in the volume (see Sharḥ Fuṣūl Ibqurāṭ ). The volume bears an owner’s note dated 761/1359. The appearance of the paper, ink, and script suggest a dating of the late seventh/thirteenth century.</note>
                     <note>The copy contains all three maqālahs, the first beginning on folio 119b, second on folio 133a and the third on folio 156a.</note>
                     <note>Dimensions 25.2 × 18.5 (text area 16.0 × 11.6) cm; 17−18 lines per page. The title is given on the title page (folio 119a) as كتاب فيه شرح تقدمة المعرفة. The author is given on folio 119b4 as Muhadhdhab al-Dīn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān [sic] ibn ʿAlī, while on the title page Ibn al-Dakhwār is added to the name. The compiler, Badr al-Dīn Muẓaffar ibn Qāḍī Baʿlabakk al-ṭabīb, is named on folio 119b3 and the person for whom it was recorded is given at folio 119b14–15 as<persName key="person_f1819">Kamāl al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥmān ibn Muslim al-ṭabīb</persName>.</note>
                     <note>The text area has been frame-ruled. The text is written in a medium-small, careful, and consistent Naskh with considerable vocalization. The letter sīn, and occasionally rāʾ , has a small háček on it; a minuscule letter occurs under the letter ḥāʾ but only very occasionally under an ʿayn. The letter kāf often, but not always, is missing the top stroke. It is written in dark brown ink with headings and overlinings in red; text-stops are small red dots, sometimes single, sometimes in groups of 3s, and sometimes enclosed in brown circles. There are no catchwords.</note>
                     <note>There are scribal corrections and later marginalia and marginal headings. Folio 118b has a table of contents for the treatise, apparently added by the writer of a note occurring on folio 119a transferring ownership to an unnamed bishop (usquf) of the three sees (karāsīy) of Amid, Mārdīn, and Tyre in the Alexandrian year of 1898 (1586): انتقل بالابتياع الشرعى ودخل خزانه كتب فقير الاساقفه بمبلغ ثلث اشرفيه خادم الثلث كراسى آمد وماردين والصور ((الطور)) وذلك بحدود سنه ١٨٩٨ يونانيه</note>
                     <note>It appears that this same writer was responsible for the repetition on the title page (folio 119a) of the name of the compiler of the treatise and the person for whom it was recorded. Karshūnī notes providing subject headings occur on folios 133a (fī al-istisqāʾ, on dropsy), 164a (fī al-buḥrānāt, on crises), and 165a (al-ruʿāf al-radī, a severe nosebleed).</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>NCAM-1, Entry No.9B</bibl>
                        <bibl>GAL I 491</bibl>
                        <bibl>UAM, 129 entry DXXXIII (533), item 2</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Thurston_10-item3" n="3" class="#commentary">
                     <locus from="168" to="168">ff. 168v-168r</locus>
                     <author key="person_f5600">
                        <persName type="standard" xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Ṭāhir ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad Ṭāhir al-Sinjārī [or Sanjarī or Shajarī], Abū al-Ḥusayn [or al-Ḥasan] (fl. c. 500/<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1106">1106)</date>
                        </persName>
                        <persName xml:lang="ar">ابو الحسن طاهر بن ابرهيم السنجرى</persName>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc">Tartīb Fuṣūl Buqrāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar-Latn-x-lc" type="alt">Tabwīb Fuṣūl Buqrāṭ</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar">ترتيب فصول بقراط</title>
                     <title xml:lang="ar" type="alt">تبويب فصول بقراط</title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt">Systematization of the Aphorisms of<persName type="standard"
                                  key="person_104252438"
                                  ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/104252438/">Hippocrates</persName>
                     </title>
                     <title xml:lang="en" type="alt">Rearrangement of the Aphorisms of Hippocrates</title>
                     <incipit>وعشرين باب رتبها ابا [= ابو] الحسن طاهر بن ابرهيم السنجرى [= السنجاري] رحمه لله وهى احسن تبويب واجمل ترتيب</incipit>
                     <explicit>الباب العشرون فى الأمراض التى تنحل وتنقضى بحدوث مرضٍ آخر فصول ١٧</explicit>
                     <note>An abridgement and reordering of the Aphorisms of Hippocrates according to topic. The copy in the Bodleian Library has only one folio, and it presents a detailed table of contents for the treatise with the heading Fihrist abwāb kitāb Ibqurāṭ (فهرست ابواب كتاب ابقراط). The author is given as Abū al- Ḥasan Ṭāhir ibn Ibrāhīm al-Sinjarī. The treatise itself is missing from the volume.</note>
                     <note>This table of contents appears to have been written by the writer of two notes dated 995/1586−7 transferring ownership of the volume to an unnamed bishop (usquf) of the three sees (thalāth karāsīy) of Amid, Mārdīn and Tyre (folios 1a and 119a). The same person also prepared the table of contents for two other Hippocratic commentaries that are preserved in the manuscript.</note>
                     <note>Dimensions 25.2 × 17.8 (text area 19 × 14 cm); 15 lines per page. The author is given as Abū al-Ḥasan Ṭāhir ibn Ibrāhīm al-Sinjarī at the beginning of the fihrist. The title of the treatise Fihrist abwāb Kitāb Ibqurāṭ is given as a heading.</note>
                     <note>The text is written in a medium-small Naskh with considerable vocalization and some ligatures; the final nūn has a small right-hand spur and there is a left-hand tick on the alifs; the letter sīn has a háček over it. The text is written in black ink with red-brown headings.</note>
                     <note>At the bottom of folio 168b a small square of paper with Turkish notes has been pasted onto the folio.</note>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl>NCAM-1, Entry No.4</bibl>
                        <bibl>UAM, 129 entry DXXXIII (533), item not described</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                     <textLang mainLang="ar">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <extent>
                           <ref target="#a1">118 ff.</ref>
                           <ref target="#a2">48 ff.</ref>
                        </extent>
                        <condition>The paper is water-stained, especially at the upper and lower edges, and slightly worm-eaten. Edges appear to have been trimmed. The outer one-quarter of folio 89 has been cut off vertically.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <additions>
                     <p>
                        <label>Paper</label>The volume is constructed of seventeen ten-leaf quires, with the beginning and ending of each quire indicated by abjad letter-numerals. The smooth beige paper has a near matt surface and a thickness of 0.17−0.21 mm with an opaqueness factor of 4. It is slightly fibrous, with horizontal straight laid lines and chain lines (slightly curved and often very indistinct) in groups of 3s; there are inclusions.</p>
                  </additions>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <p>The volume is bound in pasteboards covered with dark-brown leather with an envelope flap; possibly tenth/sixteenth-century Ottoman covers, extensively restored. The covers have blind-tooled oval medallions with blind quadrant divisions, enclosed by several blind frames enclosing two braided frames. The envelope flap has half of a blind round medallion with similar blind frames. The spine and fore-edge flap are European replacements in light tan leather. The doublure of the envelope flap is European multi-coloured marbled paper; the other pastedowns are plain paper. There are no front endpapers, but there is one modern back endpaper.</p>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <ref target="#a1">
                        <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" notAfter="1369">bef. 1369 [13th cent.?]</origDate>
                     </ref>
                     <ref target="#a2">
                        <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" notAfter="1369">bef. 1369 [13th cent.?]</origDate>
                     </ref>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>
                     <p>On folio 1a, the title page for the first item, there are six owners’ notes. What appears to be the earliest is now defaced and illegible. One note, dated Muḥarram 7[6]1<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1359">(November 1359),</date>has the name defaced but ultraviolet light reveals it to be<persName key="person_f2354">Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm al-muʿtaraf bi-Ibn al-Ṭurays</persName>; the reading of the second number in the year is uncertain. Another note, transferring ownership to<persName key="person_f4503">al-Jazarī al-Masīḥī</persName>, is dated 863/<date calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1458" notAfter="1459">1458−9</date>; on folio 119a an owner’s note bearing the same date gives the owner as<persName key="person_f4901">ʿAbd Allāh ibn al-ṣāḥib Nūr al-Dīn ibn ʿĪsá al-Jazarī</persName>and is pasted over an earlier entry with the name Ibn al-Ṭurays. A third note, possibly also by Muḥammad ibn Ibrāhīm (Ibn al-Ṭurays), is apparently dated 16 Shaʿbān 861<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1457">[9 July 1457]</date>, though the Arabic word for 800 is unclear. A fourth note transfers ownership to an unnamed bishop (usquf) of three sees (thalāth karāsīy) in the year 995/<date calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1586" notAfter="1587">1586−7</date>, also given as 1898 of the Alexandrian era; on folio 119a a similar note of ownership is recorded in which the three sees of the bishopric are specified as Amid, Mārdīn, and Tyre. The writer of the two notes dated 995/1586−7 appears to have also written the three tables of contents in the volume. On folio 1a there are also two illegible owners’ stamps and a brief note in Italian.</p>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>The volume was given to the Bodleian on<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1667">20 March 1667</date>by an unknown donor. Though now shelved as part of the collection of<persName key="person_f4346">Willian Thurston</persName>(a merchant of London, of whom little is known), the collection which bears his name consists of forty manuscripts of which only five, acquired in<date calendar="#Gregorian" when="1661">1661</date>, were actually given by Thurston. Former shelfmark: Thurston 1977,10</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Manuscript description based on Emilie Savage-Smith; A New Catalogue of Arabic Manuscripts in The Bodleian Library, University of Oxford. Volume I: Medicine, Oxford: OUP, 2011</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card (for admissions procedures contact<ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/services/admissions/">Bodleian Admissions</ref>). Contact<email>oriental@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="local_class">
               <category xml:id="commentary">
                  <catDesc>Commentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supercommentary">
                  <catDesc>Supercommentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="indices">
                  <catDesc>Indices</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="translation">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="multipleWorks">
                  <catDesc>multipleWorks</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="abridgement">
                  <catDesc>Abridgement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supplement">
                  <catDesc>Supplement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="papers">
                  <catDesc>Papers</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="documents">
                  <catDesc>Documents</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="extract">
                  <catDesc>Extract</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="gloss">
                  <catDesc>Gloss</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="selection">
                  <catDesc>Selection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="diagrams">
                  <catDesc>Diagrams</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="notes">
                  <catDesc>Notes</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="letters">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="versification">
                  <catDesc>Versification</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="#a1 #a2">
                        <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85083064#concept"
                             xml:id="subject_sh85083064">Medicine</ref>
                     </ref>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-11-07">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName>Up-converted the markup using<ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/fihrist-mss/tree/master/processing/convertFihrist2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2014-02-14">
            <persName>Lydia Wright</persName>created this file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url="folio1r.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio1v.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio2r.png"/>
      <graphic url="folio2v.png"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
