<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msdesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msdesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--  This record is intended for use in both FIHRIST and IAMS-TEI. The xml-model declarations indicate validation for FIHRIST (msdesc.rng) while the Altova XPS file indicates validation for IAMS-TEI (msdesc.sps which uses msdesc.xsd)  --><?altova_sps ..\msdesc.sps?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_32596"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Delhi Persian 1416</title><author><orgName key="fa">Persian Project</orgName></author><funder>BL</funder><principal>Ursula Sims-Williams</principal></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>British Library</publisher><date calendar="Gregorian">2022-04-21</date><pubPlace><address><addrLine>Asian and African Studies</addrLine><addrLine>British Library</addrLine><street>96 Euston Road</street><settlement>London</settlement><postCode>NW1 2DB</postCode><addrLine><ref target="http://www.bl.uk">British Library</ref></addrLine><addrLine><email>apac-enquiries@bl.uk</email></addrLine></address></pubPlace><idno>BL</idno><idno type="msID">Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416</idno><idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416" xml:lang="en"><msIdentifier><country>United Kingdom</country><settlement>London</settlement><institution>British Library</institution><repository>Oriental Manuscripts</repository><collection>India Office Library</collection><idno>Delhi Persian 1416</idno><altIdentifier type="IAMS-ID"><idno>032-004380705</idno></altIdentifier><altIdentifier type="MDARK"><idno>ark:/81055/vdc_100169708454.0x000026</idno></altIdentifier></msIdentifier><head>Miscellaneous works on poetry and prose, 9 items (a-i)</head><msContents class="http://lccn.loc.gov/sh2006003807 http://lccn.loc.gov/sh85100084"><summary>Miscellaneous collection of literary works focussing on poetry and, in margins, epistolary in prose. Volume not dated. 
Indian taʿlīq and rough taʿlīq in margins. 
Significant annotations throughout. 
Collation marks throughout. 
Discontinuous Persian foliation and in pencil. 
Lacking original binding. 
Binding of reddish brown leather, damaged (doubleurs missing, exposing roughly transcribed Persian verses and accounts on interior pasteboards), labelled. 
Loose folded paper wrapper (torn leaf extracted from EIC legal publication, unidentified); watermarked (lion rampant guardant holding sceptre in crowned oval frame; not dated); stained. 
Folios mostly unbound; cropped, wormholes, stains, some smudging of text. 
Owner’s inscriptions at beginning. 
Condition fragile. 
</summary><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><msItem n="1" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item1"><locus from="1r" to="188r">ff. 1r-188r </locus><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 a. 
</p><p>Substantial fragment of an early draft for an untitled anthology of selected excerpts from poetic compositions in varied genres and forms by various poets, ancient and modern (such as the <title key="work_22144">Kashkūl</title> of Shaykh Bahāʾ al-Dīn Muḥammad ibn Ḥusayn ibn ʿAbd al-Ṣamad al-Ḥāris̲ī al-Jubbaʾī al-ʿĀmilī al-Bahāʾī (d. 1030/1621), mas̲navī <title key="work_22144">Kharābāt</title>, <title key="work_22144">Farhang'nāmah</title>, <title key="work_22144">Muṭmaḥ al-anẓār fī al-tawḥīd</title>, <title key="work_22144">Taz̲kirat al-ʿāshiqīn</title>, <title key="work_22144">Chaman va anjuman</title>), ascribed in a statement at the beginning to <persName key="person_f3321" role="aut">Sayyid Bandah ʿAlī Qādirī takhalluṣ Bāsiṭī</persName>. 
                        </p><p>The work is organised into three chapters termed faṣl with subdivisions termed firqah, categorising works by poets, scholars, as well as rulers and courtiers, but the current copy omits any preface, introduction, or conclusion. </p><p>Summary of contents: faṣl I) list of professional poets: Ḥakīm Sanāʾī, ʿAṭṭār, Rūmī, Saʿdī, Shaykh Niẓām al-Dīn, Shaykh Abū ʿAlī Qalandar Sharaf, Shaykh ʿAlāʾ al-Dawlah Simnānī, Shaykh ʿIzz al-Dīn Maḥmūd Kāshānī, Shaykh Abū Z̲ar Buzurjānī, Shaykh Awḥad al-Dīn ʿAbd Allāh ibn Z̤iyāʾ al-Dīn Abū al-Faz̤l, Bābā Kamāl Khujandī, Shaykh Aḥmad Ghazālī, ʿAyn al-Quz̤āt Hamadānī, Shaykh Maghribī, Khvājah Ḥāfiẓ, Amīr Khusraw Dihlavī, Amīr Ḥasan Dihlavī, Jāmī, Mullā Saḥābī Astarābādī, Amīr Ḥusaynī Sādāt, Shaykh Kamāl al-Dīn Ḥusayn Khvārizmī, Shāh Dāʿī Shīrāzī, Shaykh Rūzbihān Ṣūfī, Imām Nūr Bakhsh, Mawlānā Jānī brother of Jāmī, Mawlānā Fakhr al-Dīn ʿAlī ibn Ḥusayn Vāʿiẓ Kāshifī, Khvājah Rukn al-Dīn Maḥmūd Shāh Sanjān, Pahlavān Maḥmūd ibn Pūriyā Valī, Masʿūd Bak Dihlavī, Quṭb Muḥyī, Ibn Yamīn, Mīr Muḥammad Taqī Mashhadī, Mīr Vilāyat Murīd, Khvājah Muḥammad Jaʿfar. Faṣl II) list of scholarly poets: Abū Naṣr Fārābī, Abū ʿAlī Sīnā, Naṣīr al-Dīn Muḥaqqiq Ṭūsī, Mīr Sayyid Sharīf ʿAllāmah, Mullā Jalāl al-Dīn Muḥammad Davvānī, Qāz̤ī Mīr Ḥusayn Maybudī, ʿUmar Khayyām, Shaykh ʿAbd al-Salām Payāmī, Fakhr Rāzī, Burhān al-Islām, Mullā Sharaf al-Dīn ʿAlī Yazdī, Mawlānā Ḥusayn Ardabīlī, Shaykh Shihāb al-Dīn Maqtūl, Qāz̤ī ʿAbd al-Khāliq Karah Rūdī, Mawlānā ʿAbd al-ʿAlī Tūnī, Khvājah Z̤iyāʾ al-Dīn ʿAlī Turkah, Khvājah Ṣāʾin al-Dīn ʿAlī Turkah Iṣfahānī, Sharaf al-Dīn Faz̤l Allāh Shīrāzī, Mawlānā Sharaf al-Dīn ʿAlī Bāfiqī, Mullā Abū al-Ḥasan Fāz̤il Kāshānī, Qāz̤ī'zādah Vajdān, Mīr Bāqir Dāmād takhalluṣ Ishrāq, Shaykh ʿAlī ibn ʿAṭāʾ Allāh Vaḥdat grandfather of Muḥammad ʿAlī Ḥazīn, Mullā Taqī al-Dīn Muḥammad Ḥuznī Iṣfahānī, Mīr ʿAbd al-Ghanī Tafrishī, Shaykh Muḥammad Khātūn ʿĀmilī, Mīr Abū al-Qāsim Findarsagī, Mullā Ḥasan ʿAlī ibn ʿAbd Allāh Shūstarī, Qāz̤ī Nūr Allāh Shūstarī, Mawlānā ʿAbd al-Razzāq Fayyāz̤, Shāh Ṭāhir Kāshānī known as Dakhinī, Shāh Fatḥ Allāh Shīrāzī, Mullā Muḥsin Kāshānī, Mullā Ḥasan ʿAlī Yazdī, Mullā Rajab ʿAlī Vāḥid Tabrīzī, Āqā Ḥusayn Khvānsārī, Āqā Raz̤ī Masrūr Qazvīnī, Āqā Jamāl Khvānsārī, Mīr Jaʿfar Mashhadī, Muḥammad Rafīʿ Vāʿiẓ Qazvīnī, Mullā ʿAlī Riz̤āʾ Tajallī, Mīr Muḥammad Jaʿfar Ṭihrānī, Mīrzā Ibrāhīm Hamadānī, Shaykh Ibrāhīm uncle of Muḥammad ʿAlī Ḥazīn, Shaykh Khalīl Allāh master of Muḥammad ʿAlī Ḥazīn, Ākhūnd Masīḥā Kāshānī takhalluṣ Ṣāḥibī, Mīrzā Bāqir Qāz̤ī'zādah, Ḥājī Muḥammad Gīlānī, Ākhūnd Masīḥā takhalluṣ Maʿná, Mawlānā Shāh Muḥammad Shīrāzī ʿĀrif, Muḥammad ʿAlī Ḥazīn. Faṣl III: firqah I, poets that were rulers: Shāh Ismāʿīl, Shāh Ṭahmāsp, Sām Mīrzā, Bahrām Mīrzā ibn Ismāʿīl (in margin), Sulṭān Muḥammad Mīrzā takhalluṣ Murādī, Abū al-Fatḥ Ibrāhīm Jāhī ibn Bahrām Mīrzā, Muṣṭafá Mīrzā ibn Sulṭān ʿAlī Mīrzā ibn Ṭahmāsp, Shāh ʿAbbās, Shāh Ṣafī, Shāh ʿAbbās II, Sulṭān Khudā Bandah takhalluṣ Fahmī, Rustam Mīrzā Fidāʾī, Mīrzā Murād ibn Rustam Mīrzā, Kār Kiyā Khān Aḥmad Khān ibn Sulṭān Ḥusayn, Bābur Pādshāh, Humāyūn Pādshāh, Akbar Pādshāh, Jahāngīr Pādshāh, Mīrzā Hindāl younger brother of Humāyūn, Mīrzā Abū Bakr ibn Sulṭān Abū Saʿīd Tīmūrī, ʿAskarī Mīrzā, Mīrzā Kāmrān, Sulṭān Khalīl, Sulṭān Ḥusayn Mīrzā Bāyqarā, Abū al-Muḥsin Mīrzā ibn Mīrzā Bāyqarā, Badīʿ al-Zamān ibn Mīrzā Bāyqarā, Shāh Gharīb Mīrzā ibn Mīrzā Bāyqarā, Muḥammad Muʾmin Mīrzā, Sulṭān Abū al-Qāsim, Bābur ibn Bāysunghur Mīrzā, Mīrzā Ibrāhīm ibn Mīrzā Sulaymān of Badakhshān, Sulṭān Aḥmad Bahmanī, Amīn Quṭb Shāh takhalluṣ Ẓill Allāh, Muḥammad Qulī Quṭb Shāh, Sulṭān Maḥmūd Ghaznavī, Amīr Abū Muḥammad ibn Yamīn al-Dawlah, Sulṭān ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Atsiz Saljūqī, Malik Payghū (?) Saljūqī, Sulṭān Sanjar Saljūqī, Muḥammad Yaḥyá ruler of Shīrvān, Abū al-Favāris Shāh Shujāʿ Muẓaffarī, Sulṭān Yaʿqūb ibn Ḥasan Bayg, Sulṭān Sulaymān ibn Salīm, ʿAbd Allāh Khān Ūzbak, ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz Khān, Shāh ʿĀdil Pādshāh of Lār, Qāsim ibn Naz̲r Khān Ūzbak, ʿIvaz̤ Ghāzī Sulṭān of Urganch, Ibrāhīm Khān ibn Muḥammad Khān Lārī, Mīrzā Shāh Ḥusayn ruler of Sindh, Lālah Khātūn Kirmānī, Ḥasan Bayg Shukr Ughlī Muqīmī. Faṣl III: firqah II, poets that were courtiers: Mīrzā Sanjar Niʿmat Allāhī, Mīrzā ʿAlāʾ al-Dawlah takhalluṣ Fāʾiz̤, Mīrzā Dāʾūd Mutavallī, Mīrzā Jalāl Shahristānī takhalluṣ Asīr, Amīr Niẓām al-Dīn ʿAlī Shīr takhalluṣ Fānī, Amīr Niẓām al-Dīn Aḥmad takhalluṣ Suhaylī, Amīr Ṣāliḥ, Khvājah Rashīd Hamadānī (minister of the Ilkhanid Arghūn and Khudā Bandah), Āyatī Ḥusayn, Khvājah Abū Bakr ibn Niẓām al-Mulk, Khvājah Afz̤al al-Dīn Muḥammad, Mīrzā Sharaf ibn Qāz̤ī Jahān Qazvīnī, Mīr ʿAbd al-Bāqī Niʿmat Allāhī, Mīr Qivām al-Dīn Ḥasan Ṣadr Iṣfahānī, Mīr Muḥammad Yūsuf Khalqī, Mīrzā Shāh Ḥusayn Iṣfahānī, Mīrzā Sulaymān, Mīr Muʿizz al-Dīn Muḥammad Ṣadr Iṣfahānī takhalluṣ Fayz̤ī, Mīr Shams al-Dīn Muḥammad takhalluṣ Fahmī, Khvājah Jalāl al-Dīn Amīr Bayg, Khvājah Shihāb al-Dīn ʿAbd Allāh al-Murvārīd al-Bayānī, Khvājah Ghiyās̲ al-Dīn Tangchah'ī, Iʿtimād al-Dawlah Ḥātim Bayg Naṣīrī Urdūbādī, Malik Maḥmūd Khān Daylamī, Shāh Mīr ibn Malik Maḥmūd Khān, Muḥammad Khān Iʿtimād al-Dawlah, Muḥammad Muʾmin Khān Iʿtimād al-Dawlah, Mīrzā Jalāl al-Dīn Ḥasan Ṣilāʾī Shahristānī, Mīrzā Mahdī Iʿtimād al-Dawlah, Mīr ʿAlāʾ al-Dīn Ḥusayn Khalīfah Sulṭān, Iʿtimād al-Dawlah Mīrzā Ṭāhir Vaḥīd, Ḥakīm Abū al-Fatḥ Gīlānī, Zayn Khān Kūkah, Navvāb Khānkhānān Bayram Khān, Muḥammad Khān Akbar Shāhī takhalluṣ Ghaznavī, Shaykh Fayz̤ī, Bahādur Khān brother of Khān Zamān, ʿAbd al-Raḥīm Khānkhānān, Muḥammad ʿAlī Khān Dāghistānī, Ṣadr Jahān Akbarī, S̲ānī Khān Akbarī, Khān ʿĀlam Akbarī, Bābā Dūst Ṭārumī companion of Emperor Humāyūn, Mīrzā Jaʿfar Āṣaf Khān Qazvīnī, Navvāb Qāsim Khān, Bāqir Khān Najm S̲ānī, Navvāb Ẓafar Khān takhalluṣ Aḥsan, ʿInāyat Khān Āshnā ibn Ẓafar Khān, Khān Zamān Amānī, Ḥasan Khān Shāmlū, Murtaz̤á Qulī Sulṭān Shāmlū, Ḥaydar Khān Bayglarbaygī of Marv, Muḥammad Muʾmin Bayg superintendent of the farrāsh'khānah, Shāh Virdī Khān Shāmlū, Ṣafī Qulī Bayg Nāẓir, Ughūrlū Khān Ziyād Ughlī, Najaf Qulī Bayg Mīr Ākhūr Bāshī, Muṣṭafá Khān Takkalū, ʿAbbās Qulī Khān Shāmlū, ʿAlī Qulī Khān ibn Shāh Virdī Khān, Minūchihr Khān, Ṣafī Qulī Khān ibn Z̲ū al-Fiqār Khān, ʿAlī Qulī Khān Aʿẓam, Ughūrlū Khān Shuʿlah, Murtaz̤á Qulī ibn Ḥasan Khān Shāmlū, Sayyid Mubārak Khān Madhūsh, Kay Khusraw Khān, ʿAlī Pāshā father of Islām Khān, Ḥusayn Pāshā, Navāzish Khān takhalluṣ Ṭāliʿ ibn Islām Khān ibn Ḥusayn Pāshā, Malik Abū al-Fatḥ Khān ruler of Sīstān, Malik Ḥamzah Khān ruler of Nīmrūz, Muḥammad Khān Bayg Dāghistānī takhalluṣ Hastī, Mīrzā Saʿīd al-Dīn Muḥammad Rāqim minister of Khurāsān, Mīr Jumlah Shahristānī, Mīr Maʿṣūm keeper of Bhakkar fort, Mīr Muʿizz Fiṭrat Mūsavī Khān, Imtiyāz Khān Khāliṣ, Ḥakīm Ṣadr al-Dīn Muḥammad Masīḥ al-Zamān takhalluṣ Ilāhī, Niʿmat Khān ʿĀlī, Nūr al-Dīn Muḥammad Qarārī Gīlānī brother of Ḥakīm Abū al-Fatḥ, Rukn al-Dīn Masʿūd physician to Shāh ‘Ṭahmāsp, Kamāl al-Dīn Ḥusayn ibn Rukn al-Dīn, Mīrzā Saʿīd Ḥakīm takhalluṣ Tanhā, Ḥakīm Shifāʾī, Ḥakīm Niẓām al-Dīn ʿAlī Kāshānī father of Ḥakīm Ruknā Masīḥ, Ḥakīm Ruknā Kāshī takhalluṣ Masīḥ, Shaykh Ḥusayn Shuhrat, Muʿtamad al-Mulūk ʿAlavī Khān, Ḥakīm Ḥāz̲iq ibn Ḥakīm Humām Lāhijī, Jalāl al-Dīn Muḥammad the physician, Mīrzā Muḥammad Ḥakīm Shīrāzī ibn Ḥakīm Ṣadr al-Dīn Muḥammad entitled Masīḥ al-Zamān.  </p><p>Not dated at end. </p></note><author><persName xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc" key="person_f3321">Bāsiṭī</persName><persName xml:lang="fa" key="person_f3321">باسطى</persName></author></msItem><msItem n="2" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item2"><locus from="12r" to="13r ">ff. 12r-13r and margins</locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 b. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising excerpts from selected epistolary collections, with letters entitled alqāb-i ʿamū kalān, alqāb-i ʿamū khvurd, alqāb-i birādar, alqāb-i birādar khvurd, and dar tarqīm-i ādāb. 
</p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="3" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item3"><locus from="13r" to="51v">ff. 13r-51v in margins</locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 c. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising miscellaneous passages on moral conduct, unidentified Timurid and other historical excerpts, as well as summaries of literary works. 
</p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="4" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item4"><locus from="52r" to="61v">ff. 52r-61v in margins </locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 d. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising excerpts from selected literary works (including the <title key="work_22147">Naw bāvah</title>, <title key="work_22147">Shamʿ va Chirāgh</title>), and chronogrammatic poems commemorating the nativity of princes. 
                        </p><p>Entries conclude with the colophon not fully dated (f. 61v): competed Sunday, qāʾiluhu (composer or narrator) <persName key="person_f8230" role="ctb">Mīrzā Ḥasan ibn Mīrzā Abāq Tabrīzī al-Ḥasanī al-Ḥusaynī</persName>. 
                        </p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="5" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item5"><locus from="62r" to="72v">ff. 62r-72v in margins</locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 e. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising miscellaneous excerpts of poetic compositions in varied forms and genres. 
</p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="6" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item6"><locus from="73v" to="126v">ff. 73v-126v in margins</locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 f. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising substantial excerpts of miscellaneous untitled and titled prose compositions, collections of official and private letters and petitions (including <title key="work_22149">Munshaʾāt al-ṣibyān</title> by Muḥammad Bāqir, author of first <title key="work_22149">ʿAjīb al-inshāʾ</title>, secondly <title key="work_22149">Inshāʾ-i riyāz̤-i khamsah</title>; <title key="work_22149">Khulāṣat al-makātīb</title>; <title key="work_22149">Munshaʾāt al-ṣibyān</title> by Shāh Khākī), chronogrammatic poems, revenue calculations in raqm; some anonymised entries are dated internally to the years 1146/1733, 1166/1752, etc. 
                        </p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="7" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item7"><locus from="128v" to="141r">ff. 128v-141r in margins</locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 g. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising miscellaneous poetic compositions in varied forms and genres (such as the chronogrammatic qiṭʿah on the death of <persName key="person_f8231" role="subject">ʿUmdat al-Mulk Amīr Khān</persName>), others attributed to <persName key="viaf_14200302" role="att">Āṣafī</persName> and <persName key="viaf_51467595" role="att">Kātibī</persName>. 
                        </p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="8" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item8"><locus from="141v" to="151v">ff. 141v-151v in margins</locus><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 h. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising excerpts from selected literary works (including an untitled epistolary collection by Bindrāban through the instruction of Shāh Khākī). 
</p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem><msItem n="9" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_1416-item9"><locus from="152r" to="186r">ff. 152r-186r in margins</locus><author><persName xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc" key="ark:/81055/vdc_100164657506.0x000001 viaf_43428948">Ṭālib</persName><persName xml:lang="fa" key="viaf_43428948">طالب</persName></author><note><p>Delhi Persian 1416 i. 
</p><p>Untitled annotations comprising miscellaneous poetic excerpts, mostly lyrics or ghazalīyāt in alphabetic order, by a poet bearing the takhalluṣ Ṭālib. 
</p><p>Not dated at end. 
</p></note><textLang mainLang="fa" otherLangs="ar">Persian and Arabic </textLang><note /></msItem></msContents><physDesc><objectDesc form="codex"><supportDesc material="chart"><extent>188 ff. <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm"><height>239</height><width>156</width></dimensions></extent></supportDesc></objectDesc><handDesc><handNote script="Arabic" scope="sole" /></handDesc></physDesc><history><origin notBefore="1752" notAfter="1753"><origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1752" notAfter="1753">1752 - 1753</origDate><origPlace>India</origPlace></origin><provenance><p>Purchased by the Government of India at sale organised by Delhi Prize Agents, 1859; administrative deposit India Office Library, 1876 </p></provenance><acquisition><date>1876</date><p>Government of India </p></acquisition></history><additional><adminInfo><availability status="free"><p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/reshelp/inrrooms/stp/register/stpregister.html/">British Library, Registering for a Reader Pass</ref>. Contact <email>apac-enquiries@bl.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript. For information on catalogues and ordering manuscripts see <ref target="https://www.bl.uk/help/find-persian-manuscripts">Finding and ordering Persian manuscripts in the British Library</ref>.
                        </p></availability></adminInfo></additional></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="LCSH"><bibl><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="#LCSH"><list><item><term key="subject_sh2006003807" target="http://lccn.loc.gov/sh2006003807#concept">Sufi literature, Persian</term></item><item><term key="subject_sh85100084" target="http://lccn.loc.gov/sh85100084#concept">Persian poetry</term></item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2022-04-21"><persName>Julian Cook</persName>
              850 BL Persian mss prepared for initial publication in FIHRIST (plus 18 replacements)
         </change><change when="2018-02-28">Sāqib Bāburī</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><!-- Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription --></p></body></text></TEI>