<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msdesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msdesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- This record is intended for use in both FIHRIST and IAMS-TEI. The xml-model declarations indicate validation for FIHRIST (msdesc.rng) while the Altova XPS file indicates validation for IAMS-TEI (msdesc.sps which uses msdesc.xsd) -->
<?altova_sps ..\msdesc.sps?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_18561">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Delhi Persian 662</title>
            <funder>BL</funder>
            <principal>Ursula Sims-Williams</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>British Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="Gregorian">2022-04-21</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Asian and African Studies</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>British Library</addrLine>
                  <street>96 Euston Road</street>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <postCode>NW1 2DB</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.bl.uk">British Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>apac-enquiries@bl.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>BL</idno>
            <idno type="msID">Uk_Delhi_Persian_662</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <settlement>London</settlement>
                  <institution>British Library</institution>
                  <repository>Oriental Manuscripts</repository>
                  <collection>India Office Library</collection>
                  <idno>Delhi Persian 662</idno>
                  <altIdentifier type="IAMS-ID">
                     <idno>032-004341443</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
                  <altIdentifier type="MDARK">
                     <idno>ark:/81055/vdc_100163233768.0x000033</idno>
                  </altIdentifier>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Miscellaneous works on Sufism, doctrine, and ritual, 24 items (a-x)</head>
               <msContents class="http://lccn.loc.gov/sh2008112367 http://lccn.loc.gov/sh2006003807">
                  <summary>Miscellaneous collection of works on Sufism, doctrine, and ritual by or ascribed to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName>, who entitles the volume <title>Kitāb Alifah</title> (see item c). Defective at end. Volume not dated; item b and g dated (5 Muḥarram-17 Ṣafar 1082/14 May-25 June 1671) separately; all items share similar paper and range of scribal hands and are, therefore, likely to be the product of a single scriptorium at <placeName>Akbarābād</placeName> (<persName>Agra, UP, India</persName>) by several scribes under the author’s patronage. Neat ornamental naskh with occasional taʿlīq flourishes, or scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz, by at least three identified hands. Limited annotations in margins. Stamped and Persian foliation. Lacking original binding. Binding severely damaged (decorative printed paper exterior pasteboards with brown leather spine; delaminating inner matter exposing texts in Kaithi, Persian, Arabic, early Urdu), labelled. Folios mostly unbound; cropped, wormholes, later repairs. Condition very fragile. 
                  </summary>
                  <msItem n="1" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item1">
                     <locus from="1v" to="12r">ff. 1v-12r</locus>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item a. </p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on demonstrations of love for the <persName key="viaf_97245226" role="subject">Prophet Muḥammad</persName> through celebrations of his birth or mawlūd. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Copious passages in Arabic. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. 
</p>
                        <p>Other works (items b-c) transcribed in margins, by the same hand. 
</p>
                        <p>The work begins with a basmalah in ornamental naskh. 
Text in neat naskh slackening towards the end. 
</p>
                        <p>Notes on flyleaves. </p>
                     </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian &amp; Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="2" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item2">
                     <locus from="1v" to="7v">ff. 1v-7v margins</locus>
                     <author>
                        <persName xml:lang="per-Latn-x-lc" type="supplied" key="person_f7374">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName>
                     </author>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item b. </p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on the death of the <persName key="viaf_97245226" role="subject">Prophet Muḥammad</persName> by <persName key="person_f7374" role="aut">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName>, author of <title>Hidāyat al-Hind</title>, an abridgement of the <title>Ḥujjat al-Hind</title>. 
                        </p>
                        <p>The work begins with a basmalah in ornamental naskh. 
</p>
                        <p>Neat naskh with occasional taʿlīq flourishes, written obliquely in an intermediate column between items a and c. 
</p>
                        <p>Dated colophon (f. 7v): completed by <persName key="person_f7029" role="scr">ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn Khvājah Muḥammad Qāsim</persName> at <placeName>Akbarābād (Agra)</placeName>, 17 Ṣafar 1082/25 June 1671. 
                        </p>
                     </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="3" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item3">
                     <locus from="1v" to="1v">f. 1v margin</locus>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item c. </p>
                        <p>Arabic note describing the assembly of the present volume, entitled <title>Kitāb Alifah</title>, as the work of <persName key="person_f7374" role="aut">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī al-Naqshbandī</persName>. 
                        </p>
                        <p>Naskh in outermost column of margin along right edge. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <author>
                        <persName xml:lang="per-Latn-x-lc" key="person_f7374" type="supplied">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName>
                     </author>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="4" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item4">
                     <locus from="8r" to="8r">f. 8r margin</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item d. </p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise explaining a Prophetic ḥadis̲ on the benefits of remembering death. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Basmalah in nastaʿlīq. Neat ornamental naskh with occasional taʿlīq flourishes, written obliquely in margin. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="5" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item5">
                     <locus from="12r" to="13r">ff. 12r-13r panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item e. </p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on the virtues of the last Friday in the lunar Hijrī month of Ramaz̤ān. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Nastaʿlīq with tendencies to combine naskh and taʿlīq; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="6" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item6">
                     <locus from="13r" to="13v">ff. 13r-13v panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item f. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on virtues in the recitation of the <title>Qurʾān</title> in the lunar Hijrī month of Ramaz̤ān. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Small nastaʿlīq with tendencies to combine naskh and taʿlīq; text following into margins. </p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="7" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item7">
                     <locus from="13v" to="19r">ff. 13v-19r</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item g. 
</p>
                        <p>Arabic Sufi treatise on the sanctity of the lunar Hijrī months of Rajab, Z̲ū al-Qaʿdah, Z̲ū al-Ḥijjah, and Muḥarram. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>The work begins with a basmalah in neat and expressive ornamental naskh continued throughout. 
</p>
                        <p>Dated colophon (f. 19r): completed by <persName key="person_f7029" role="scr">ʿAbd al-Raḥīm ibn Khvājah Muḥammad Qāsim ibn Ḥāfiẓ Dūst Muḥammad Andijānī</persName> at <placeName>Akbarābād (Agra)</placeName>, on the morning of Friday, 5 Muḥarram 1082/14 May 1671.
                        </p>
                     </note>
                     <title xml:lang="per-Latn-x-lc" key="work_22235">Bāb fī faz̤āʾil Rajab</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="8" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item8">
                     <locus from="14r" to="17r">ff. 14r-17r margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara" otherLangs="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item h. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise describing circumstances on Yawm al-Qiyāmah or the Day of Judgement. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Small nastaʿlīq written obliquely in margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="9" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item9">
                     <locus from="17r" to="17r">f. 17r margin</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item i. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi note instructing on the virtues of reciting <title>Durūd-i Muʿaẓẓam</title>. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Small nastaʿlīq written obliquely in the margin. </p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="10" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item10">
                     <locus from="17r" to="17r">ff. 17r margin</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item j. 
</p>
                        <p>Arabic prayer, <title>Durūd-i Muʿaẓẓam</title>, in praise of the Prophet Muḥammad. This is not attributed to Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Ornamental naskh written obliquely in the margin. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="11" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item11">
                     <locus from="19v" to="21v">ff. 19v-21v panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item k. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on the virtues of almsgiving or zakāt and categories of Muslims upon whom it is an obligation. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>The work is divided into three faṣl. 
</p>
                        <p>Substantial quotations in Arabic. 
</p>
                        <p>Nastaʿlīq with tendencies to combine naskh and taʿlīq; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                     <author/>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="12" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item12">
                     <locus from="21v" to="24r">ff. 21v-24r </locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item l. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on the sanctity of the precinct of <placeName>Mecca</placeName>. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                     <author/>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="13" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item13">
                     <locus from="24v" to="30r">ff. 24v-30r</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item m. 
</p>
                        <p>Sufi treatise on the isrāʾ and miʿrāj or nocturnal journey to the <placeName>Masjid al-Aqṣá</placeName> and ascent to heaven of the <persName key="viaf_97245226" role="subject">Prophet Muḥammad</persName>, as well as the virtues of its annual commemoration in prayer and fasting. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>In one of the margins is a note referencing the <title>Miftāḥ al-jannah</title> (here <title>
                              <sic>Miftāḥ al-janān</sic>
                           </title>) of <persName key="viaf_90051632" role="oth">Jalāl al-Dīn Suyūṭī</persName> (d. 911/1505). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Nastaʿlīq with tendencies to combine naskh and taʿlīq; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                     <title xml:lang="per-Latn-x-lc" key="work_22236">Risālah dar bayān-i miʿrāj va faz̤āʾil-i ān shab</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="14" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item14">
                     <locus from="56r" to="66v">ff. 30r-32r panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item n. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on the sanctity of s of Rajab, Shaʿbān (with particular emphasis), Ramaz̤ān, and Muḥarram. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Nastaʿlīq with tendencies to combine naskh and taʿlīq; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="15" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item15">
                     <locus from="32r" to="41r">ff. 32r-41r panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item o. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on the virtues of fasting and elective prayers, especially during the lunar Hijrī month of Ramaz̤ān. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Small nastaʿlīq with tendencies to combine naskh and taʿlīq; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="16" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item16">
                     <locus from="41r" to="42r">ff. 41r-42r panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item p. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on the mode of salutation of seventy thousand angels lead by <persName key="person_f7201" role="subject">Jibrāʾīl</persName> or <persName key="person_f7201" role="subject">Gabriel</persName> descending in the presence of the <persName key="viaf_97245226" role="subject">Prophet Muḥammad</persName>. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Small scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins. </p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="17" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item17">
                     <locus from="42r" to="45r">ff. 42r-45r panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item q. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on the virtues of festivities or ʿĪd associated with the early Prophets <persName key="viaf_89660956" role="subject">Ibrāhīm</persName> or <persName key="viaf_89660956" role="subject">Abraham</persName>, <persName key="ark:/81055/vdc_100164656093.0x000001 viaf_100646822" role="subject">Mūsá</persName> or <persName key="ark:/81055/vdc_100164656093.0x000001 viaf_100646822" role="subject">Moses</persName>, <persName key="ark:/81055/vdc_100164657205.0x000001 viaf_38323081" role="subject">ʿĪsá</persName> or <persName key="ark:/81055/vdc_100164657205.0x000001 viaf_38323081" role="subject">Jesus</persName>, and finally the <persName key="viaf_97245226" role="subject">Prophet Muḥammad</persName>. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="18" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item18">
                     <locus from="45r" to="45v">ff. 45r-45v panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item r. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on a prophetic tradition relating to <persName key="viaf_30328354" role="subject">Fāṭimah</persName>, daughter of the <persName key="viaf_97245226" role="oth">Prophet Muḥammad</persName>. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="19" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item19">
                     <locus from="45v" to="45v">ff. 45v margin</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item s. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on sleep in relation to the ritual prayers. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="20" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item20">
                     <locus from="45v" to="46v">ff. 45v-46v panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item t. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Arabic Sufi treatise on sleep in relation to the ritual prayers. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="21" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item21">
                     <locus from="46v" to="47v">ff. 46v-47v panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item u. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on the virtues of fasting in the lunar Hijrī month of Ramaz̤ān, with verses. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins.
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="22" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item22">
                     <locus from="48r" to="50v">ff. 48r-50v panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="ara">Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item v. 
</p>
                        <p>Arabic Sufi treatise on the virtues and obligations of Friday. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                     <title xml:lang="per-Latn-x-lc" key="work_22237">Risālat faz̤āʾil va masāʾil yawm al-Jumʿah</title>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="23" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item23">
                     <locus from="51r" to="55r">ff. 51r-55r panel and margins</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item w. 
</p>
                        <p>Untitled Sufi treatise on the virtues the tenth day of the lunar Hijrī month of Z̲ī al-Ḥijjah in addition to Abrahamic traditions. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Scribal nastaʿlīq with tendencies to shikastah āmīz; text following into margins.
</p>
                        <p>Colophon at end not dated (f. 55r): completed by <persName key="person_f7371" role="scr">Muḥammad ʿIvaz̤</persName>. 
                        </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem n="24" xml:id="Uk_Delhi_Persian_662-item24">
                     <locus from="55r" to="56v">ff. 55r-56v</locus>
                     <textLang mainLang="per" otherLangs="ara">Persian and Arabic</textLang>
                     <note>
                        <p>Item x. 
</p>
                        <p>Incomplete fragment of an untitled Sufi treatise encouraging the practice of sacrifice and z̲ibḥ or ritual slaughter in association with to Abrahamic traditions. Although the author is not mentioned, it is attributable to <persName key="person_f7374" role="att">Muḥammad Jān ibn Muḥammad Ṣiddīq ibn Ḥāfiẓ Sulṭān Maḥmūd Tāshkandī Naqshbandī</persName> based on the testimony of a note on the first page (item c). 
                        </p>
                        <p>Defective at end. 
</p>
                        <p>Not dated at end. </p>
                     </note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="chart">
                        <extent>56 ff. (+1)<dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>245</height>
                              <width>157</width>
                           </dimensions>
                           <dimensions type="written" unit="mm"/>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote script="Arabic" scope="major"/>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin calendar="Hijri-qamari" notBefore="1671-05-14" notAfter="1671-06-25" when-custom="5 Muḥarram-17 Ṣafar 1082">
                     <origDate calendar="Hijri-qamari" notBefore="1671-05-14" notAfter="1671-06-25">5 Muḥarram-17 Ṣafar 1082 (14 May 1671 - 25 June 1671)</origDate>
                     <origPlace>Akbarābād</origPlace>, <placeName>Agra, UP, India</placeName>
                     <origPlace>India, Agra</origPlace>
                  </origin>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Based on unpublished description in Catalogue of Persian Manuscripts in the India Office Library, vol. 3. Available on British Library Digitised Manuscripts, manuscript number: <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/manuscripts/Viewer.aspx?ref=mss_eur_e207!29_f017r">MSS Eur E207/29_f017r</ref>
                        </source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/reshelp/inrrooms/stp/register/stpregister.html/">British Library, Registering for a Reader Pass</ref>. Contact <email>apac-enquiries@bl.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript. For information on catalogues and ordering manuscripts see <ref target="https://www.bl.uk/help/find-persian-manuscripts">Finding and ordering Persian manuscripts in the British Library</ref>.
                        </p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl>
                        <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/manuscripts/Viewer.aspx?ref=mss_eur_e207!29_f017r">MSS Eur E207/29_f017r</ref>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh2006003807" target="http://lccn.loc.gov/sh2006003807#concept">Sufi literature, Persian</term>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <term key="subject_sh2008112367" target="http://lccn.loc.gov/sh2008112367#concept">Sufism--Early works to 1800</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-04-21">
            <persName>Julian Cook</persName>
              850 BL Persian mss prepared for initial publication in FIHRIST (plus 18 replacements)
         </change>
         <change when="2017-03-31">
            <persName key="person_f7748" role="cataloguer">Sāqib Bāburī</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>
            <!-- Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription -->
         </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
