<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msdesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/msdesc/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--  This record is intended for use in both FIHRIST and IAMS-TEI. The xml-model declarations indicate validation for FIHRIST (msdesc.rng) while the Altova XPS file indicates validation for IAMS-TEI (msdesc.sps which uses msdesc.xsd)  --><?altova_sps ..\msdesc.sps?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_32464"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>RSPA 31</title><principal>Ursula Sims-Williams</principal><funder>BL</funder><sponsor /><author><orgName key="fa">Persian manuscripts Project</orgName></author><editor>Jonathan Lawrence</editor></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>British Library</publisher><date calendar="Gregorian">2022-04-21</date><pubPlace><address><addrLine>Asian and African Studies</addrLine><addrLine>British Library</addrLine><street>96 Euston Road</street><settlement>London</settlement><postCode>NW1 2DB</postCode><addrLine><ref target="http://www.bl.uk">British Library</ref></addrLine><addrLine><email>apac-enquiries@bl.uk</email></addrLine></address></pubPlace><idno>BL</idno><idno type="msID">Uk_RSPA_31</idno><idno type="catalogue">Fihrist</idno></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc xml:id="Uk_RSPA_31" xml:lang="en"><msIdentifier><country>United Kingdom</country><settlement>London</settlement><institution>British Library</institution><repository>Oriental Manuscripts</repository><collection>India Office Library</collection><collection>Jones Collection</collection><collection>Royal Society Arabic and Persian</collection><idno>RSPA 31</idno><altIdentifier type="other"><idno>XXXI</idno><note>Royal Society number</note></altIdentifier><altIdentifier type="former"><idno>84a</idno><note>Charles Wilkins' catalogue number</note></altIdentifier><altIdentifier type="IAMS-ID"><idno>032-003475895</idno></altIdentifier><altIdentifier type="MDARK"><idno>ark:/81055/vdc_100097964683.0x000003</idno></altIdentifier></msIdentifier><head /><msContents class="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100085"><summary>1 copy of Khamsah-'i Niẓāmī by Niẓāmī Ganjavī</summary><textLang mainLang="fa">Persian</textLang><msItem n="1" xml:id="Uk_RSPA_31-item1"><locus from="1v" to="411r" /><title xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc" key="work_20054">Khamsah-'i Niẓāmī</title><title xml:lang="fa" key="work_20054">خمسۀ نظامی</title><author><persName xml:lang="fa-Latn-x-lc" key="ark:/81055/vdc_100166919744.0x000001 viaf_177843849">Niẓāmī Ganjavī</persName><persName xml:lang="fa" key="viaf_177843849">نظامی گنجوی</persName></author><incipit xml:lang="fa">پیش وجود همه آیندگان *** پیش بقای همه پایندگان</incipit><explicit xml:lang="fa">برا وباد قرخنده بر نام او *** ز آغار او تا با نجام او</explicit><note><p>A copy of the Iskandar-nāmah which does not separate the text into two parts. The text of Iskandar-nāmah is also very different from the standard (modern printed) edition; the differences from the Sprenger edition (completed by 1869) are indicated throughout the text of the Iskandar-nāmah in pencil marginal annotations by a modern hand.</p><p>Jones notes on f1r, "I bought this fine copy of Niẓāmī for 100 S.R. the seller having at first demanded 200. 11 April, 1788 W Jones" and, in Persian, "مالک این کتاب یر ولیام یونس یکی از حاکمان عدالت عالیه پادشاهی در شهر کلکته قیمتش صد روپیه" Above these notes, there are two large notes which state this book had been the property of Mīr Muḥammad Bāqir.</p><p>Jones makes extensive annotations and marginal comments on the Haft Paykar exclusively. This text he annotates for linguistic reasons (in both Persian and English) and he writes notes about the story and the miniatures. As for the other texts, he also writes out their title and the metre of the poem on each of their first pages. On f144r, the second page of Majnūn Laylī, he notes in Persian: "من بیدل وراه بیماکست چون را هبرم توئی چباکست". Jones also makes two important notes outside of the textblock; on fiv verso, he notes the seven parts of the story of Haft Paykar and on f411v, he notes in a circular shape the names (right to left, top to bottom): Firdawsī, Mavlavī, Saʿadī, Anvarī, Ḥāfiẓ and Niẓāmī. His annotations and comments on Haft Paykar are too numerous to list and warrant some extensive study.</p></note><decoNote type="illustration">18 miniatures in the Shiraz style of about 1575: f4v, f55v, f97r, f120v, f160v, f179r, f205r, f228v, f239v, f248r, f251v, f256r, f261r, f268r, f273v, f334r, f356r and f394v. See B.W. Robinson, Persian paintings in the India Office Library, London, 1976, nos. 324-341</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.4b The ‘Mi‘raj’ or Heavenly Ascent of the Prophet, mounted on Buraq, led by Gabriel, and attended by four other angels. The figures are large, four of the angels' faces and that of Buraq have been deliberately damaged, and the outer edge of the miniature is somewhat blackened. 21 by 17 cm (plus banner in upper margin).</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.55b Khusraw spies Shirin bathing. Smaller figures. Khusraw is accompanied by a young footman. 22 by 15 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.97a Farhad carrying Shirin and her horse over a rocky ridge, her mounted maids watching in astonishment. 16 by 15.5 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.120b Entertainment given in a garden pavilion by Khusraw to a number of ladies; Shirin-shares his throne, while two others are seated on separate chairs. A little trimmed and blackened at the outer edge. 22 by 19 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.160b Majnun at the Ka‘ba with his father and other pilgrims. A trifle blackened at the outer edge. 19 by 16.5 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.179a Majnun in the wilderness comforted by his father, whose seated camel occupies a prominent position in the composition. 17.5 by 14.5 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.203a Layla and Majnun fainting. One or two of the faces have been damaged and the miniature is blackened along the upper and outer edges. Large figures. One man defends himself with a sword against an attacking wolf. 19 by 17 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.228b Bahram Gur killing the lions to win the crown. The miniature is very slightly blackened along the lower part of the outer edge, and one of the lions has been damaged. 19.5 by 15.5 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.239b The Black Pavilion. The Indian princess is represented as dark-skinned, though all her maids are white. 15 by 16.5 (plus dome in upper margin).</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.248a Illustration to the beginning of the story told by the princess in the Yellow Pavilion. Buying slaves for the King of ‘Iraq. 17.5 by 15 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.251b Bahram Gur in the Green Pavilion with the princess of the Fourth Climate. Slight patches of blackening. 21 by 15 cm (plus dome in upper margin).</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.256a Bahram Gur and the princess in the Red Pavilion. Some blackening towards the top of the miniature and upper margin (with dome) trimmed. 17.5 by 15 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.261a Bahram Gur and the princess in the Blue Pavilion. Actually the prevailing colour is apple-green, and the heading calls it ‘gunbad i zard’ ('the yellow dome'). 19.5 by 15 cm (plus dome in upper margin).</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.268a Illustration to the beginning of the story told by the princess in the Sandalwood Pavilion. The two youths Good and Bad, carrying packages, setting out from their city, watched by others from the wall and horizon. 12.5 by 15.5 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.273b Bahram Gur and the princess in the White Pavilion. The faces of Bahram and two of the attendant maids have been damaged and clumsily redrawn. The outer edge somewhat blackened. 16.5 by 15.5 cm (plus dome in upper margin).</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.334a The marriage of Iskandar and Rushanak: her face and that of one of the attendant maids have been damaged, and the outer edge somewhat blackened. 21.5 by 17 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.356a Presentation of gifts from King Kaid of Hind to Iskandar. The face of Iskandar is slightly damaged, and the outer edge somewhat blackened. 18.5 by 17 cm.</decoNote><decoNote type="illustration">f.394 Iskandar and the Seven Sages, one of whom, at the foot of the throne, holds an astrolabe. The colours have oxidized in several parts of the miniature. 19.5 by 14.5 cm.</decoNote></msItem></msContents><physDesc><objectDesc form="codex"><supportDesc material="chart"><support>Thin cream woven paper.</support><extent>ff.iv+411+iii
                <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm"><height>340</height><width>220</width></dimensions><dimensions type="written" unit="mm"><height>220</height><width>120</width></dimensions></extent><foliation><p>European numerals in pencil.</p></foliation><condition><p>Good condition. Some damage to miniatures.</p></condition></supportDesc><layoutDesc><layout columns="4" writtenLines="16"><p /></layout></layoutDesc></objectDesc><handDesc hands="1"><summary>Beautiful nastaʿlīq in black ink.</summary><handNote script="Arabic" scope="major" /></handDesc><decoDesc><decoNote type="initial">Opening (f1v-2r) consists of illuminated blue and gold headpiece with floral design. The first folio of each individual poem is also adorned with a large headpiece and illuminated (gilded) textboxes. Headings in floral gilded boxes.</decoNote></decoDesc><additions><p>Extensive annotations and marginal comments on the Haft Paykar.</p><p>There are scribal marginal notes throughout the manuscript.</p></additions><bindingDesc><p>Standard India Office half leather binding with wine coloured marbled endpapers.</p></bindingDesc><accMat><p /></accMat></physDesc><history><origin notBefore="1550" notAfter="1575"><origDate calendar="Gregorian" notBefore="1550" notAfter="1575">1550 - 1575</origDate><origPlace>Iran</origPlace></origin><provenance><p>Former owner: Mīr Muḥammad Bāqir. RSPA 1-118 were presented to the Royal Society in January 1792 by Sir William and Lady Jones. This manuscript was given by Sir William Jones.</p><p>The Royal Society's collection of 280 Persian and Arabic, and 86 Sanskrit manuscripts were transferred to the India Office Library in 1876.</p></provenance><acquisition><date>1876</date><p>India Office Library</p></acquisition></history><additional><adminInfo><recordHist><source>Manuscript description based on E. Denison Ross and E. G. Browne, Catalogue of two collections of Persian and Arabic manuscripts preserved in the India Office Library (London: Eyre and Spottiswoode, 1902), p.26-8 no. XXXI</source></recordHist><availability status="free"><p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.bl.uk/reshelp/inrrooms/stp/register/stpregister.html/">British Library, Registering for a Reader Pass</ref>. Contact <email>apac-enquiries@bl.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript. For information on catalogues and ordering manuscripts see <ref target="https://www.bl.uk/help/find-persian-manuscripts">Finding and ordering Persian manuscripts in the British Library</ref>.
                        </p></availability></adminInfo><surrogates /></additional></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><classDecl><taxonomy xml:id="LCSH"><bibl><ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords scheme="#LCSH"><list><item><term key="subject_sh85100085" target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100085#concept">Persian poetry--747-1500</term></item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change when="2022-04-21"><persName>Julian Cook</persName>
              850 BL Persian mss prepared for initial publication in FIHRIST (plus 18 replacements)
         </change><change when="2020-02-05" /></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div /></body></text></TEI>